<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mans whole duty and Gods wonderful intreaty of him thereunto set forth from 2 Cor. 5, 20, and published at the request of some hearers / by Daniel Burgess.</title>
            <author>Burgess, Daniel, 1645-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 178 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 89 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30282</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5709</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23833</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07915466</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07915466</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40387</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30282)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40387)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1199:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mans whole duty and Gods wonderful intreaty of him thereunto set forth from 2 Cor. 5, 20, and published at the request of some hearers / by Daniel Burgess.</title>
                  <author>Burgess, Daniel, 1645-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 168 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Richardson for Tho. Parkhurst, and John Lawrance,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Licensed according to order."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 2nd, V, 20 --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40387:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40387:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Mans whole Duty, AND Gods wonderful Intreaty Of him thereunto.</p>
            <p>Set forth from 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. and Publiſhed at the Requeſt of ſome Hearers.</p>
            <p>By <hi>DANIEL B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGESS,</hi> Miniſter of the Word of Reconciliation.</p>
            <p>Licenſed according to Order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Richardſon</hi> for <hi>Tho. Park<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide;</hi> and <hi>John Lawrance</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in the <hi>Poultry.</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:40387:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40387:2"/>
            <head>To my Excellent Friends,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Joan Wood.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Anne Hook.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Abigail Vanittern.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Martha Brown.</item>
               </list> OF THE CITY OF BRISTOL.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlewomen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THeſe Lines do not vainly deſign to <hi>adorn</hi> your Names; but are very uprightly meant to <hi>defend</hi> my own, from
<pb facs="tcp:40387:3"/>one of the <hi>blackeſt</hi> Reproaches. Even loathſome <hi>Ingratitude.</hi> I have bid them tell all they meet, that <hi>You</hi> were, for ſome (black) years together, my nobleſt <hi>Gaia's:</hi> And your <hi>Houſes,</hi> my ſweet <hi>Homes.</hi> That I am not <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankful,</hi> though I am <hi>Inſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent.</hi> That I am not <hi>Inſolvent</hi> neither, if <hi>Prayers do diſcharge Debts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do continue my pleaſant <hi>Hope</hi> of your Perſons Reconciliation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God: And my <hi>Prayers</hi> for your Deareſt Relatives: Beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Father of Glory, to make his own Love, the Reward of Yours unto me. And if it he his bleſſed pleaſure, to make theſe very <hi>Leaves</hi> bear ſome <hi>Fruit</hi> unto your Souls</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:40387:3"/>
            <p>Be it freely ſaid, as far as I know my ſelf, I am neither <hi>Proud</hi> nor <hi>Aſhamed</hi> of them. Not <hi>Proud;</hi> for I am aware how my imperfections do <hi>Blemiſh</hi> them. Not <hi>Aſhamed;</hi> for I am told, God hath <hi>Bleſſed</hi> them; and I am made to believe, that he <hi>will Bleſs</hi> them. That as they are not <hi>Beautiful,</hi> ſo neither ſhall they be <hi>Barren,</hi> as <hi>Rachel.</hi> But <hi>Fruitful,</hi> though <hi>Blear-Eyed</hi> as <hi>Leah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have told you ſome Years ago, that I Preached for the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of <hi>Plow-Boys and Milk-Maids,</hi> as well as <hi>Lords and Ladies.</hi> And if I did not, I ſhould never expect to do ſo much upon them by <hi>Rhetorical Polite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:40387:4"/>as by <hi>Goſpel Plainneſs.</hi> Honey Dews be ſweet to the Taſt, but they miſerably blaſt the Corn. <hi>Delights of Fancy, hinder Wounds of Heart.</hi> This is ſtill my Thought.</p>
            <p>And if you are ſtill the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> that I once knew you, I am ſure you will welcome <hi>Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Goſpel.</hi> 'Tis Goſpel I do preſent you, and in Dreſs as homely as I heretofore uſed among you. I am not now firſt to <hi>crave a Bleſſing</hi> upon it; but ſhall ever <hi>continue</hi> craving it: And particularly a Bleſſing to your ſelves, and to the <hi>Olive-Plants</hi> about your Tables.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Clare-Houſe,</hi> in <hi>Drury-Lane, Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> 
                  <date>Dec. <hi>11. 1689.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Affectionate Orator un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Heavenly Father.</hi> D. Burgeſs.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40387:4"/>
            <head>Man's whole Duty, and God's wonderful Intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of him thereunto.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>II COR. V. 20.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Be ye Reconciled to God.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>OUR <hi>Being</hi> is our leaſt and loweſt Honour and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. The end of all Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, is <hi>Action.</hi> But neither is that its own End, or our Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Action, is for the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Being; as our Being is for our employment in Action. Work deſigns <hi>Reward;</hi> and that together perfecteth our Action and Being. The Reward that doth
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:40387:5"/>this, is the Jewel ineſtimable; which ſhould be bought at any rate, but ſold at none. And this, whether blind men ſee it or no, is <hi>Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am ſure, <hi>Divels and Damned ghoſts</hi> do feel it. They are weary of their Beings; and have no Action but in unallayed torments; becauſe they neither Love nor are Loved. They are ſtill uneaſie, and in degrees of pain proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned to their Enmity. <hi>Holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and the Spirits of the Juſt above, do alſo feel it.</hi> Their Eſſence and Action are as ſweet as they wiſh; becauſe their Love is as great as they can deſire. Their Love is an Ocean, and therefore is their Joy not a drop leſs. <hi>This middle Worlds Inhabitants,</hi> as far as they have their Senſes, do feel it too. The <hi>dead in ſin,</hi> do prefer their impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Loves above their Lives. And all that are <hi>alive unto God,</hi> do ſet
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:40387:5"/>their Seals unto that Glorious Truth, and moſt memorable: <hi>He that dwelleth in Love dwelleth in God, and God in him.</hi> 1 Jo. 4.16.</p>
            <p>With profoundeſt Reverence be it writ and read! <hi>The Divine Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs it ſelf, which hath no limits, doth conſist in Love.</hi> The <hi>Perſons of the Glorious Trinity</hi> are bleſſed infinitely. Their Being and Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing are as much <hi>ſweeter</hi> unto them, as they are <hi>greater</hi> then any Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. And this, becauſe they Love and are Beloved mutually, no leſs then infinitely. Were their Love of each other but finite, their Delight and Pleaſure muſt be as imperfect. The reaſon is moſt plain; Loving and being Loved, is all the Pleaſure of an intelligent Nature.</p>
            <p>Wherefore to ſeek our Happy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs any where but in Love, its very Element; is to leave the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and go fiſh in the Woods. And to doubt whether we ſhall find Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40387:6"/>in Love, is to make a queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whether when we come to Sea, we ſhall find any Water there?</p>
            <p>I am by ſad Experience cured of my haſty Confidence, as truly as ever great <hi>Melanchton</hi> was. Nor do I preſume I ſhall win all my Readers of this Eſſay. I expect not to take and hold all the <hi>Fiſh</hi> that come to this <hi>Goſpel-net</hi> it ſelf: But I muſt have leave to ſay, I do expect a very <hi>good Draught.</hi> For I ſhall propoſe a word, that will coſt Men hard ſervice to reſiſt. You that are <hi>fartheſt from the Kingdom of God,</hi> will have much ado to get away Unconvert: And you that ſtand <hi>nigher,</hi> muſt fight with all your might and main, if you be not led captive to Chriſt this time. So extraordinary a portion of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture, is that which I here offer. A <hi>Text</hi> call it if you pleaſe. I do account it, and call it, <hi>all the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40387:6"/>Bible in eight Syllables.</hi> The ſum and ſubſtance of all God thinks fit to Speak, and that we need to Hear.</p>
            <p>Three things are obvious in it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Mans miſerable condition.</hi> He is an Enemy to God. He could not otherwiſe be adviſed to Reconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Gods merciful Condeſeention.</hi> To Prepare and Offer a Reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation: Yea, and beſeech our Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Mans dutiful Religion.</hi> No hard task, nothing of brick and bondage: Only to be friends and Reconciled to God.</p>
            <p>Or, if you like, ſee you now, and never look off again while you live; ſee here two particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) <hi>The Richeſt Feaſt that Grace it ſelf can prepare.</hi> Very Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation unto God.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:40387:7"/>(2.) <hi>The Sweeteſt Invitation that it can make unto the ſame.</hi> Even Obſecration and Intreaty, by Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, by Chriſt, and by the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God. By <hi>King, Prince</hi> and <hi>Embaſſadors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now cloſe your Ears, if you can, againſt this Doctrine.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Reconciliation to God is the whole Duty of Man, and ſinful Man is intreated thereto by God.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>The Heads of Diſcourſe that offer themſelves are,</p>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>Mans Duty.</hi> Of which, in our <hi>Doctrinal</hi> part.</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>Gods Intreaty.</hi> Of which, in our <hi>Application.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt ſhall have its <hi>Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in five orderly Poſitions; And its <hi>Proof,</hi> by as many demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40387:7"/>Arguments, as ſhall appear needful.</p>
            <p>Poſition 1. <hi>God and Man were once entire Friends. Likeneſs</hi> to God, qualified for ſuch Friendſhip. And Gods bleſſed <hi>Love,</hi> both ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily and freely followed that likeneſs. <hi>Till Sin entred, Man was as like to God, as God willed: And as dear to God, as he himſelf could will or wiſh.</hi> For, as to <hi>Relation,</hi> he was made his Son; <hi>Luk.</hi> 3.38. As to <hi>Portion,</hi> God gave him all things; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.6. As for <hi>Tenure,</hi> he held all by Covenant; and was ſure to loſe nothing till he ſhould ſin it away; <hi>Gen</hi> 2.17. As for <hi>Covenant,</hi> he had it ſign'd and ſeal'd. The Trees of Life and of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge were Sacramental; <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.9. And as to <hi>Communion,</hi> doubtleſs that was great between <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Adam;</hi> till <hi>Adam</hi> made himſelf a <hi>fugitive,</hi> and God made him an <hi>exile.</hi> For ought we know, it was
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40387:8"/>not much leſs between <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradiſe, then between <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Angels. Large Minds have thought, the ſin of the Angels, was their Envy at the Honour by God given unto Man.</hi> While Man was himſelf, without all peradventure he would rather have been annihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, then conſented to <hi>one</hi> vain thought. And as ſoon have cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to live in a boyling Cauldron of Oyl, as any <hi>courſe</hi> of ſin. But,</p>
            <p>Poſ. 2. <hi>Sin made God and Man extreme Enemies.</hi> At one blow it deſtroy'd, the <hi>Likeneſs,</hi> the <hi>Love,</hi> the <hi>Relation,</hi> the <hi>Portion,</hi> the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> the <hi>Communion</hi> aforeſaid. Of Father and Son, it made them as Fire and Water. Contrary to each other. <hi>Juſtice</hi> armed God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Man, and Malice enraged Man againſt God. Righteouſly, God curſed Man; and no doubt but Man bitterly, curſed and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed God. Had not our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40387:8"/>interpoſed, God would have aſſoon embraced a <hi>Divel</hi> as a <hi>Man.</hi> And before <hi>Christ</hi> was preached unto <hi>Adam,</hi> I queſtion not, but he wiſh'd the deſtruction of his Creator. In a word; The Scriptures declare God, and every unconvert Man, while ſuch, at open war, and at utmoſt enmity. Before that <hi>Abels</hi> be converted, God does hate them; and more then <hi>Cains</hi> do hate them afterward. Neither doth any <hi>Cain</hi> hate his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as they hate their Maker. No Souls do near ſo much hate their Neighbours, as all Unregenerate ones do hate their God. Lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able truth! Till Chriſt makes the bleſſed Peace, God and Men wage the worſt War. And there's no more concord between God and Men, then between God and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels.</p>
            <p>Poſ. 3. <hi>God and Man ceaſe not to be Enemies, till they both return to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40387:9"/>be entire Friends again.</hi> Friendſhip is mutual Love. 'Tis but <hi>Love,</hi> not <hi>Friendſhip,</hi> where both parties do not Love. <hi>Enmity</hi> alſo, is mutual <hi>Hatred.</hi> Nor is it <hi>Enmity,</hi> but <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred</hi> only, when but one of the parties do hate. Accordingly, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation</hi> is mutual; and cannot be ſaid to be made, if both Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies return not from their <hi>Hatred</hi> to <hi>Love:</hi> Yea, and unto that height and <hi>very degree</hi> of Love from whence they fell. A diſplaced Bone is not right ſet, if it be not brought again into the very place whence it was thruſt; nor will it ever be eaſie or comely. Reconciliation to God is not right, nor will it be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, without his <hi>Condeſcention</hi> to us, and our <hi>Aſcenſion</hi> unto him, made as in the beginning. The things forenamed muſt be regained; to wit, our <hi>Likeneſs, Love, Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Portion, ſigned, ſealed Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> and <hi>Communion.</hi> Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40387:9"/>is full Reſtoration.</p>
            <p>Poſ. 4. <hi>Reconciliation between God and Man hath ſeven memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things relating to it.</hi> It concerns thoſe that deſire any part and por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in it, to bear always in mind theſe things of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Gods Purpoſe and Promiſe of it, from all Eternity. Before the foundation of the World,</hi> God pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to reconcile ſome Enemies; <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.4, 5. <hi>Before the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan,</hi> he made a promiſe of the ſame unto his Son; <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.2. To wit, in thoſe Eternal Tranſactions that were between the <hi>Father</hi> and the <hi>Son,</hi> by their one Eternal <hi>Spirit.</hi> Whereof we read, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.22. to 32. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.10, 11, 12. &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Jeſus Chriſts Purchaſe of it, at his Death.</hi> The Holy <hi>Goſpel</hi> certifies us, that Chriſt by his Death <hi>purchaſed</hi> Reconciliation for ſome ſinners: <hi>Paid the whole price</hi> for it, and <hi>procured</hi> that it ſhould in Gods
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40387:10"/>time be given forth unto them. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.14.</p>
            <p>It has been ſaid, that ſin made God and Man extream Enemies. Let it be conſidered, that God could never <hi>Purpoſe</hi> or <hi>Promiſe</hi> a Reconciliation, but in a way con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the honour of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. And conſequently, through a full <hi>Satisfaction</hi> made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, for all the Glory that our ſin took from him: And a <hi>Price</hi> truly valuable paid unto him, for all the Favours beſtown upon us. Now to make ſuch Satisfaction, and to pay ſuch Price, was infinitely above the power of any <hi>meer</hi> Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. To invent it, was beyond the compaſs of finite underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. To ask it, had been too in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent a boldneſs. To effect it, was moſt perfectly impoſſible. Dr. <hi>Owens Diatribe de Juſtitia Vindictiv.</hi> and Dr. <hi>Bates</hi> his <hi>Harmony of the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes of God in our Redemption;</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:40387:10"/>abundantly clear this. I ſay but this word or two.</p>
            <p>A meer Creature could not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly make and pay it, by <hi>Doing</hi> or <hi>Suffering.</hi> Not by <hi>Doing:</hi> For it can do nothing for God, but what it owes unto God. And if it could, yet it could not do ſo much, as would repay the Glory that ſin robs God of: For <hi>One, the</hi> leaſt ſin, <hi>takes more Glory from God in a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute, then all our Obedience would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore in our everlaſtingneſs.</hi> Becauſe our Obedience doth in no ſort pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit him; and gives but little honour to him; as preferring him but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove poor Creatures themſelves: But our ſin, in many reſpects, doth reproach and injure him horribly, as to his manifeſtative Glory, caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an unmeaſurable Contempt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him; as ſetting him with all his infinite Excellencies under every Creatures feet. Nextly; not by <hi>Suffering:</hi> For a Creature cannot
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40387:11"/>ſuffer <hi>infinitely,</hi> as ſin deſerves, but by ſuffering <hi>endleſly.</hi> Now if it ſo ſuffer, it muſt be alwayes <hi>making;</hi> it will not ever <hi>have made</hi> the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction we ſpeak of. It will be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>paying</hi> the price; but it will never <hi>pay</hi> the full payment. Alas, <hi>it is certain, that Hell would have ſome end, if the Creatures own tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for a million of years could ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie for one ſin!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore, it pleaſing God to <hi>purpoſe</hi> the reconcilement of ſinful Men unto himſelf; and there being a neceſſity it ſhould be upon terms <hi>Honourable</hi> unto him, as well as <hi>Beneficial</hi> unto us; it pleaſed him to <hi>purpoſe</hi> and <hi>promiſe</hi> that it ſhould be through his Incarnate Sons fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid <hi>purchaſe,</hi> and meritorious <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curement.</hi> God was in Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling the World to himſelf; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. In Chriſt, as his Oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for us, and as his Gift unto us. The Oblation that ſatisfied his Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40387:11"/>for us; the Gift that ſatisfied his Love unto us, (as a great hand expreſſeth it.) So 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6. <hi>He,</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>gave himſelf a Ranſom for all;</hi> and <hi>Coll.</hi> 1.14. <hi>We have Redemption through his Blood.</hi> A Myſtery indeed; the Myſtery of Myſteries; and which engageth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakably our regards of the next particular concerning this Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation unto God: To wit,</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The Holy Ghoſts proof of it.</hi> For of Sinners reconciliation unto God; we are ready to think the news <hi>too good to be true.</hi> To cry out, How can it be? I, and when we are told, it is to be through a full ſatisfaction made by his Son; and price invaluable paid by him. By him, who, though the <hi>infinite God,</hi> became a <hi>finite Man:</hi> Tho' <hi>Gods equal,</hi> became his <hi>Servant:</hi> Though the <hi>Bleſſed God,</hi> yet was made <hi>a Curſe</hi> for us: We cannot but perſiſt asking, <hi>How can theſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40387:12"/>things be?</hi> It nothing repents me, that I have often ſaid; <hi>We do now as much need to have the Spirit of God Live in us, as ever we did need the Son of God to Dye for us.</hi> And as the Purchaſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation did require a Divine Perſon, the Proof of it doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire no leſs.</p>
            <p>God deals with Man, as Man: In a way of Reaſon, ſuited unto his Reaſonable Nature. Which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Believe any thing, without a Reaſon for Belief of it. Of all the great and marvellous things that God commands our Faith, he firſt giveth <hi>ſufficient grounds</hi> for our Faith of them. Particularly, of his foreſaid <hi>Purpoſe</hi> to reconcile Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and of his Sons <hi>Purchaſe</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; things of greateſt <hi>worth</hi> and <hi>weight;</hi> and of Concernment to as many as do need Reconciliation. Of theſe extraordinary things, God hath provided extraordinary <hi>Proof.</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:40387:12"/>Even the Teſtimony of a Perſon, no leſs than the Father himſelf, or the Son. Of the Glorious Spirit, coeſſential and coequal with both. This Divine, Infallible Perſon, who cannot be deceiv'd himſelf, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive us; is ſent by the Father and his Son, to certifie us of the <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe</hi> and the <hi>Purchaſe</hi> which we ſpeak of. To inform us of both; to conquer and drive away the <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections</hi> of our Minds againſt both; to give us a certain kind of <hi>preſence</hi> and <hi>ſight</hi> of both. A <hi>ſight</hi> ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to move our <hi>Wills,</hi> and make our <hi>Hearts</hi> to relye and reſt upon both as really true. And to draw our <hi>Affections</hi> in neceſſary degrees; cauſing us to Love and long for the <hi>poſſeſſion</hi> of the Reconcilement ſo <hi>purpoſed,</hi> and ſo <hi>purchaſed.</hi> And to over-rule our <hi>Lives;</hi> and make them nothing ſo much, as a courſe of <hi>Contemplation, Prayer</hi> and <hi>Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> for this ſaid Reconciliation.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40387:13"/>For, be it deeply conſidered;</p>
            <p>The <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> is declared in the Word, to be ſent for this end; To be a <hi>Witneſs</hi> unto Jeſus Chriſt, and an <hi>Agent</hi> for him. It would be very vain to object that <hi>the Holy Spirit was given under the Old Teſtament long before Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt came to Reconcile us by his Death.</hi> For he was ſo upon Chriſts interpoſing as our Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler ſtraight-way after ſins entrance; and that with reſpect to Chriſts fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>Oblation</hi> and <hi>Interceſſion</hi> for our Reconcilement. And then as for <hi>degrees,</hi> there is no compariſon. <hi>The Spirit drop'd but Dews in the Old Teſtament: In the New, he rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed down Showers.</hi> So that comparate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he is ſaid not to be given till Chriſt was Glorified. He, our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, comes into the World, and proclaims Gods <hi>Love</hi> unto it, and <hi>purpoſe</hi> to reconcile and ſave ſinners: As alſo his own <hi>undertaking,</hi> (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40387:13"/>to a <hi>contract</hi> made between the <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>himſelf,</hi>) to effect that Reconciliation by his <hi>Oblation</hi> and <hi>Interceſſion.</hi> This, the guilty graceleſs World could not <hi>believe;</hi> nor have the <hi>patience</hi> to hear, from the reputed Son of a Carpenter. <hi>Jews</hi> as well as <hi>Gentiles,</hi> made light of it; yea, roſe in arms againſt it; all, ſave a handful; and thoſe bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter taught by him, whom we are next to ſpeak of. The Holy <hi>Spirit</hi> (as was agreed on between the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſons,</hi>) now cometh; and what does he? Why, he guides Souls into the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> and <hi>Faith</hi> of all the Truth by Chriſt preach'd. He <hi>Glorifies Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> convinceth Unbelievers that Chriſt is no <hi>Impoſtor,</hi> but a <hi>Glorious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> come with a <hi>Glorious Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> to purſue Gods <hi>Glorious Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,</hi> and to make the <hi>Glorious Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe</hi> foreſaid. He receiveth Chriſts Spiritual things, and ſhews them
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40387:14"/>unto Men that could not ſee them before; even his <hi>Truth</hi> and his <hi>Grace.</hi> He receiveth them from <hi>Christ,</hi> as the <hi>Lord Treaſurer</hi> of them; and ſhews them abroad, that it may be ſeen, <hi>what they are,</hi> and <hi>in whoſe hand they are:</hi> That Glory may be brought unto Chriſt: That he may be owned and honoured as the <hi>Purchaſer</hi> of the <hi>purpoſed</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation; <hi>Jo.</hi> 16.13, 14, 15. &amp;c. This did the bleſſed Spirit effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally; cauſing the Church in all Ages to exalt the <hi>Father</hi> as the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal <hi>Purpoſer;</hi> the <hi>Son,</hi> as the Meritorious <hi>Purchaſer;</hi> the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> as the convincing <hi>Proof-maker</hi> of our Reconciliation. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which Proof, no Soul had ever <hi>believed</hi> it, or found an Heart to <hi>look after</hi> a portion in it: Which is the next great Conſideration con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning it. For, if God has <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed,</hi> and Chriſt has <hi>Purchaſed</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation; and the Holy Ghoſt
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40387:14"/>has <hi>proved</hi> it ſo fully, that there is no juſt place for the leaſt doubt, but they have ſo done; the very next thing to be looked after muſt be,</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>The Sinners poſſeſſion of it.</hi> For whatever be the <hi>proportion</hi> of a good, it avails not me without <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety.</hi> Let this Reconciliation be thought, as it is in truth, a good no leſs than <hi>infinite.</hi> If it be not made <hi>mine own;</hi> if I am not Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled; the <hi>ſound</hi> of its Doctrine is to me, but as the <hi>ſpeech</hi> of Bread, to a Man ſtarving for want of it: Or as <hi>words</hi> of a Pardon, to a Man going up the Ladder, when he hath it not.</p>
            <p>O what <hi>Pillows</hi> do they ſleep on, who lay their Eyes together with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this Reconciliation attained? <hi>One would think it ſhould be more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to rest on the points of ſwords and ſpears, then upon one thought of God unreconciled.</hi> I will ſay with my
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40387:15"/>dear, and now bleſſed Friend, Mr. <hi>Richard Alleyn</hi> of <hi>Somerſet-ſhire: If all the Kings of the Earth would give me all they are worth; I would not lie down on my bed any night with one ſin <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrepented, and without ſome hope of God Reconciled to me!</hi> But I return.</p>
            <p>The Holy Spirit in his Word te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifyeth, a <hi>purpoſe</hi> of Reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that is Eternal: As alſo a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation</hi> at the Death of Jeſus Chriſt, that is <hi>Fundamental.</hi> But he doth as clearly deny any <hi>actual Reconciliation,</hi> before <hi>Converſion:</hi> Before our Underſtanding and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Conſent unto the Covenant of Grace. How ſhould Divine Wif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom throw the richeſt Pearl to the vileſt Swine? Or Holineſs forgive and embrace Creatures contrary to it? There is no Law above God, but God is a Law to himſelf: And though he can do what he will, he cannot will what is Unwiſe or Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40387:15"/>Elect, or not Elect, <hi>he that believeth not on the Son, the wrath of God abideth on him.</hi> Jo. 3.36. <hi>He that hath not the Son of God,</hi> (to wit, in Marriage-Covenant;) <hi>he hath not Life;</hi> (to wit, the Life of <hi>Peace</hi> with God, or of <hi>Hope</hi> from him, or of <hi>Holineſs</hi> toward him.) 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.12. In a word: Look at what time God <hi>teacheth,</hi> and you <hi>learn;</hi> at what time God <hi>draws,</hi> and you <hi>run</hi> after him; at what time you unfeignedly ſay, <hi>Lord, I do rely on the promiſes, and I do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the demands of the Goſpel-Covenant;</hi> at that time, in that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry punct of time, your Pardon is ſeal'd in Heaven. 'Tis publiſhed in the Goſpel, and declared ſo to be. For you are told; <hi>He that hath the Son of God hath Life;</hi> 1 Joh. 5.12. <hi>There is no condemnation to them that are in Christ Jeſus;</hi> Rom. 8.1. And <hi>being juſtified by Faith you have peace with God through our
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40387:16"/>Lord Jeſus Christ;</hi> Rom. 5.1.</p>
            <p>Come <hi>Reader,</hi> come take Eternal Life from theſe Lines! Hold thy ſelf not a minute longer in Hell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire; for Gods wrath is not a jod leſs. Down with my Book; and down fall thou on thy Knees, and utter the few words, which will make God and thy Soul everlaſting Friends. No longer dare to live. Damned. Venture to ſtrike the Goſpel-Covenant, and be ſaved! Say to Jeſus Chriſt; <hi>Lord, I will stay no longer, I am thine upon thy Goſpel-terms for ever. From this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant to Eternity, I will be thine. Say to thy ſelf; Heart, bid an eternal a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieu unto <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs, and unto trust in ſelf-righteouſneſs as ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory or meritory. Say unto vain Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; Sirs, I take my leave of you; I must travel no farther with you, that are not for the ſtrait gate and narrow way. If you will not be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to God with me, I will not
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40387:16"/>any longer ſight against God with you.</hi> But whither do I break?</p>
            <p>Be it known unto every Reader, this is Goſpel: <hi>God is not Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to us FOR our Repentance and Faith.</hi> The moſt penitent Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, are but unprofitable ſervants unto him. <hi>But he is never to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled WITHO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T Repentance and Faith.</hi> Both are as <hi>neceſſary,</hi> as tho' they were <hi>Meritory;</hi> though they are infinitely far from it. Yea, <hi>and upon the first penitent and faithful conſenting to the Goſpel-Covenant, God and Sinners become as</hi> true <hi>Friends as God and Holy Angels.</hi> And as <hi>Eternally inſeparable</hi> ones; <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.38, 39. 'Tis not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed or concealed: The <hi>grant</hi> of Peace is one thing, and the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of it is another: And theſe two are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable. God may be Reconciled to a Covenant-ſervant of his for months and years, and the ſervant be in fear and doubt of it. <hi>Thoſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40387:17"/>ſins that hinder not Gods grant of Peace to us, do often hinder our ſenſe and aſſurance of it.</hi> Wherefore, we are to conſider another particular concerning Reconciliation: To wit,</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>The Believers perſwaſion of it.</hi> For, though Reconciliation be the greateſt good; though it be Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally <hi>purpoſed</hi> for me; and by Chriſts Death <hi>purchaſed</hi> for me; and be by the Holy Spirit <hi>proved</hi> to me, that it is for ſome Purpoſed and Purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Yea, though through Grace I am <hi>poſſeſſed</hi> of it, what then? Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til I know that I am poſſeſſed of it, I am but like a <hi>Child in the Womb:</hi> Living indeed in a bag of water, but not knowing my own Life. I have a Life that is only in <hi>degree</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour to the Life of Angels: But yet I live in doubts and fears, that I am like unto Divels; and that I ſhall lodge for ever in their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable fire. Now be it care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40387:17"/>heeded: The Holy Spirit who is given to <hi>work</hi> Grace in us, he is alſo given to <hi>witneſs</hi> Grace unto us; and to <hi>make us know the things that are freely given to us of God;</hi> 1 Cor. 2.12. He is a free and ſoveraign Agent indeed; and he works and witneſſes (in them, in whom he worketh,) <hi>as he pleaſeth.</hi> He giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth aſſurance of Peace with God, <hi>as much</hi> as he pleaſeth; and <hi>as ſoon,</hi> and <hi>no more,</hi> and <hi>no ſooner,</hi> than he pleaſeth; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.11. At the firſt Plantation of the <hi>Goſpel-Church,</hi> he uſed together to <hi>convert</hi> Souls, and to <hi>aſſure</hi> them of their Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation unto God. But now we ſee, he doth not ordinarily ſo do. And as commanded, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.10. moſt Converts do give <hi>great dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,</hi> before their <hi>Election and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation are made ſure.</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn the <hi>Roman Synagogue,</hi> that meaſures all Cloth by its own Ell; and denyeth the attainableneſs of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40387:18"/>that aſſurance, which they neither duly <hi>ſeek,</hi> or ever <hi>attain.</hi> Our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines have confuted and ſhamed them ſo much, that there needs not any thing to be ſaid unto their blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous Dreams. Let the deſirous Reader ſee but that one moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Sermon of Mr. <hi>Samuel Fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clough</hi> on 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lectures againſt Popery. The Churches of Chriſt do believe and teach, that the bleſſed Spirit doth <hi>ordinarily,</hi> ſooner or later, witneſs unto true Converts their Reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation: And ſeal them to the day of Redemption.</p>
            <p>And this, either <hi>mediately</hi> or <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately. Immediately,</hi> by a ſort of <hi>ſpiritual words:</hi> Such as paſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and the Bleſſed Spirits above. By theſe the Holy Ghoſt teſtifieth unto humble diligent Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, that they are Gods Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled and Adopted Children. And when he doth ſo, he doth it with a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40387:18"/>
               <hi>clearneſs</hi> and <hi>ſweetneſs</hi> that carry their own evidence with them. For there is no Rule beyond it, by which it may be tryed, as there is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther viſible, beſides the Light it ſelf, whereby you may try it; <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16. He is ſaid therefore <hi>to witneſs with our Spirits, that we are the Children of God.</hi> And <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.13. with <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.30. He is ſaid to <hi>ſeal us:</hi> But how ſo? Unleſs he doth ſet ſome print and ſtamp upon us, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing our ſtate and Relation. Again, <hi>mediately</hi> the Spirit perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth us alſo of our Reconciliation. To wit, by enabling us to ſee our Graces <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>ſincerity;</hi> and from thence to infer our certain Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation. Both wayes he is <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily</hi> the Comforter of ſound Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers.</p>
            <p>I have read of a Woman that would ſay, ſhe had born eight or nine Children; and with as much pain as other Women uſed to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo:
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:40387:19"/>But ſhe would be content to bear all that pain over again for this comfort of the Spirit. O that the ſame <hi>mind</hi> were in all that <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs</hi> a value of it! But well; what if you had ſought and found it too? There's another very material par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular concerning Reconciliation to God, that would ask for your thoughts and cares: To wit,</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>The practical improvement of it.</hi> I mean of his <hi>Reconciliation,</hi> and of his <hi>perſwaſion</hi> or aſſurance of it. Hear the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.2. <hi>Having theſe promiſes,</hi> (to wit, of Reconciliation and all Grace, <hi>chap.</hi> 6. latter end;) what uſe are we to make of them? Why, <hi>Let us cleanſe our ſelves from all fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs of Fleſh and Spirit, perfecting holineſs in the fear of God. q. d.</hi> 
               <q>Let us live, as far as we can, without ſin. Let us do Gods will on Earth as 'tis done in Heaven, unto our utmoſt ability. Let us
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40387:19"/>do all we are able to make our Reconciliation more honourable to God then our Damnation would have been.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Aſſurance, is a ſpecial <hi>priviledge.</hi> Scarce <hi>any</hi> Childs portion, at <hi>all</hi> times. And <hi>'tis poſſible that ſome of Gods Children may live and dye with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it.</hi> However, when it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow'd, extraordinary <hi>Aids</hi> of Grace and <hi>Advantages</hi> for Duty are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed with it. The helps which School-Men call <hi>neceſſary,</hi> are given to all that are Converted: But thoſe which they call <hi>liberal,</hi> are given but to them that are Aſſured. In Converſion, all Gods Children do receive ſtrength ſufficient to walk <hi>acceptably</hi> with him: But when they are ſealed by the Holy Spirit, they receive additional ſtrength to walk <hi>more ſerviceably.</hi> Now as <hi>more</hi> is given to them, <hi>proportionably</hi> more is required from them; more than from <hi>other Converts,</hi> that are not yet
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40387:20"/>aſſured of their Peace with God. <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.48. <hi>Every Iſraelite owed God much; but the Nazarite owed him much more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If I were asked, <hi>Who of all the living were deepest Debtors unto God, and had moſt work ſet them to do.</hi> I would ſay, <hi>aſſured Chriſtians!</hi> Yea, and I verily think, that next unto Saints <hi>Glorified,</hi> none are ſo pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and ſo humble as the <hi>aſſured.</hi> True it is, in many things they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves do offend: And 'tis not in Perfection <hi>attained,</hi> but <hi>expected,</hi> that the beſt of them dare to glory. Wherefore their Eye is, at leaſt it ought to be ever kept, upon the laſt particular concerning our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation unto God. And that is,</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>The Judgment days publication and perfection of it.</hi> Acts. 3.19. <hi>Sins ſhall be,</hi> in open Court, <hi>blotted out,</hi> when that <hi>day of refreſhment cometh from the preſence of the Lord.</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:40387:20"/>Reconciliation ſhall be publiſhed to purpoſe, when in the audience of Men and Angels, God the Judge of all ſhall pronounce it with his Mouth. And ſo, that he will be <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired in his Saints and all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.</hi> To wit, for the heights whereto he exalteth them, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.10. Hear but one Apoſtle more; 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.2. <hi>When he ſhall appear we ſhall be like him:</hi> That is, when God diſplays his own Glory in the Son of his Love; who comes at the laſt day <hi>in the Glory of his Father;</hi> we ſhall be as like him as ſhall be fit for Children to be like a Father. There ſhall be no ſign of any variance ever being betwixt us: But all the <hi>Bleſſedneſs</hi> poſſible ſhall ſpeak his perfect Reconciliation to us, and all the <hi>Holineſs</hi> poſſible ſhall ſpeak our like Reconciliation unto him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whether the ſins of Believers ſhall be all of them publiſhed in the general Judgment,</hi> is a Queſtion. Learned
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40387:21"/>
               <hi>Alting</hi> brings five Reaſons for the <hi>Affirmative,</hi> and as many for the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative.</hi> But it is moſt undoubted, that the bleſſed Friendſhip betwixt God and them, ſhall be then ſhewn abroad through the whole Creation; and be exalted beyond the reach of our preſent words or thoughts!</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Auſtins</hi> Mother, hearing a Sermon of Heaven, is reported to have cryed out; <hi>O what do I here in this World?</hi> Methinks <hi>Reader,</hi> thou ſhouldſt imitate her. And here exclaim; <hi>O what have I to do all my days, but provide for this Judgment-day?</hi> Wouldſt thou know what courſe to take for this proviſion; I beſeech thee attend unto the fifth and laſt Poſition, that I offer for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicating my Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Poſ. 5. <hi>Mans buſineſs touching his Reconciliation unto God, falls into three particular exerciſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Attention,</hi> Reader, <hi>Attention;</hi> give here thy <hi>beſt Attention;</hi> and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40387:21"/>the greateſt thou ever gaveſt, to the things that beſt deſerve it. <hi>Theſe Exerciſes muſt be thine, if ever the war between God and thee do come to an end.</hi> The war lies in this, which of you ſhall have their will. Fain <hi>thou</hi> wouldſt have thy own will, as bad an one as it is. As <hi>mad</hi> a Mind as 'tis led by. I mean, as void as 'tis of <hi>Truth,</hi> and as poſſeſſed as 'tis with <hi>Error. Self-will is the ſin of ſin.</hi> It lives longeſt and dyes laſt, in every ſinner. Fain wouldſt <hi>thou</hi> live, as thou liſteſt; Think, ſpeak, and act, as thou pleaſeſt; have thy Thoughts and Works alſo free: Fain wouldſt thou be thy own <hi>Man,</hi> yea, and <hi>God</hi> too. Making to thy ſelf no God, but thy ſelf; and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving no <hi>Law</hi> but thy <hi>Luſt.</hi> I, and after this done, thou wouldſt not be undone. <hi>Thou</hi> wouldſt gain this in the World, and not loſe thy Soul; take the Hell <hi>in</hi> ſin, and miſs the Hell prepared <hi>for</hi> it. Thou
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:40387:22"/>wouldſt <hi>Temporally</hi> and <hi>Eternally</hi> disjoyn the evil of <hi>Suffering</hi> from the evil of <hi>Doing.</hi> And eſcape that, though thy Life be ſpent, to the laſt breath of it, in this. But <hi>God</hi> ſaith thee <hi>nay;</hi> and ſends forth <hi>Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> to the contrary. From him I have Commiſſion to tell thee; and I do by theſe Preſents give thee to know; <hi>God will tear Heaven and Earth in pieces, and (if it could be) he would himſelf dye in the fight, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than thou ſhouldſt have that will of thine.</hi> Rather, then thou thy ſelf ſhouldſt eſcape the <hi>miſery</hi> of Divels, if thou wilt hold their <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity,</hi> and keep unreconciled as they. Yea, and rather than he will ever afford thee <hi>Reconciliation,</hi> in any way but that of his <hi>Goſpel-Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If therefore thou learn'ſt not, and falleſt not unto theſe Goſpel-Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes that I am commending, thou plainly thus ſpeakeſt; <q>To Hell,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:40387:22"/>
                  <hi>my Soul,</hi> get thee going to Hell. <hi>O extremity of torment,</hi> I will ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture thee! <hi>O eternity of anguiſh,</hi> I fear thee not! <hi>O Worm, that ever livest, and O Fire that never dyeſt,</hi> I will bear you both! And <hi>O you exerciſes that are the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots of Grace and Eternal Glory,</hi> I tell you all three, I ſcorn you!</q> Frightful words; and not to be heard without amazement, and a quaking Heart!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> were I to beg but one Bleſſing for my own Soul, and for thoſe that are deareſt unto me, it ſhould be this: That we might hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily <hi>begin</hi> and <hi>hold on</hi> theſe three Exerciſes. Whereof I ſhall treat as <hi>plainly</hi> and <hi>fully,</hi> though as <hi>briefly</hi> as I am able. Take them together firſt, thus. They are,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Of Believing and Conſidering Reconciliation,</hi> in reſpect to the three firſt particulars. That is, <hi>as pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:40387:23"/>as purchaſed, and as proved to be ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Of praying and labouring for Reconciliation,</hi> in reſpect to the three next particulars: That is, <hi>as poſſeſſed, as perſwaded or aſſured of, and as practically improved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Of hoping for Reconciliation, and rejoycing in it,</hi> in reſpect to the laſt particular: That is, <hi>as publiſhed and perfected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here, obſerve thou well; how far it is from <hi>brick</hi> and <hi>bondage</hi> whereto thou art called. <hi>Idleneſs, is of the worſt wracks, that an Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Soul can be ſet on;</hi> and thou art called to <hi>employment</hi> right ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable. Thy <hi>Labour</hi> is not deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, till admirable encouragements unto it are <hi>known,</hi> and well <hi>conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered</hi> firſt by thee. No, nor till ſuperabundant aids from Heaven are <hi>invoked.</hi> Thou art not ſet to Labour, but in <hi>Hope,</hi> and for or
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40387:23"/>with <hi>Joy</hi> unſpeakable and full of glory. The World deals quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary with its Vaſſals. In the ways of ſin, Men <hi>know</hi> not whither they go, and are not ſuffered to <hi>conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> what they are like to have for their Labour. And indeed their <hi>Labour</hi> is to ſow in much pain what they reap in Eternal Torment. In their Lives and Labours, as in their Deaths, they have no <hi>Hope;</hi> or what is worſe than none. They are far from <hi>Joy;</hi> the Spirit of God aſſures us, there is no Peace to them. And their Mirth is nothing in the world but light-headedneſs. <hi>Their going to Play-houſes, is but ſending themſelves to Bedlam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Come on then, and learn the <hi>way,</hi> and enter into the <hi>joy</hi> of the Lord. The Lord that ſends me to invite thee, and thus direct thee.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Thou muſt believe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that Sinners Reconciliation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God is a thing purpoſed by God,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:40387:24"/>purchaſed by Chriſt, and proved to be ſo by the Holy Ghost.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have ſhewn it to be ſo. But O Man! <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandeſt thou what thou readeſt?</hi> I have proved it by Authority of Sacred Scriptures; but alas, <hi>Believeſt thou the report of them?</hi> It is ſcarce every hundredth Man of thoſe who <hi>own</hi> them, that doth in truth <hi>believe</hi> them. So judg'd the great <hi>Calvin</hi> himſelf. And the truth is, if in any thing it be hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then other to credit Divine Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it is in its Teſtimony unto this great Truth. Nevertheleſs ſo it is, that its Teſtimony herein muſt be <hi>credited</hi> ſincerely, and <hi>conſidered</hi> of ſeriouſly, before we can be quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for <hi>Chriſtianity:</hi> That is, for Jeſus Chriſts reconciling and ſaving Religion. For the embracing it with ſeriouſneſs and ſincerity, unto our Reconciliation and Salvation. <hi>Who can charge his Conſcience with all reſpects to a Religion, whoſe first
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:40387:24"/>Principles and very Foundations he is ignorant or doubtful of?</hi> Who can purſue it whatever it coſts him, and give it the Government of his Life and Soul? They who do any leſs, do but dally with Religion; they do not uſe it like it ſelf. And they who do ſo much, need to be very well certified of the goodneſs of the grounds they go upon. If not, they muſt continually be like to Builders, who doubt their Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ill laid; and therefore either by and by <hi>deſist</hi> from their work, or <hi>go on very heartleſly</hi> with it.</p>
            <p>Thus therefore muſt thou do, whoever thou art that deſireſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation unto God. With a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity ſuitable to the moment of the affair, thou muſt go and enquire into theſe things: Namely, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou haſt Faith.</hi> And, if thou haſt, <hi>What a Faith it is that thou haſt,</hi> concerning the things foreſaid. Alas, <hi>Sin is diſtractive:</hi> And Minds
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:40387:25"/>ſinfully diſtracted, do conceit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to believe, whatever they do not in words contradict. Nor do they at all diſcern the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Moon-light</hi> and <hi>Sun-ſhine.</hi> Though the former be cold, and diſpel no Vapours, and ripen no Fruits, as the latter doth by its e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually uſeful and beautiful Beams. They diſtinguiſh not between the <hi>Hiſtorical</hi> and <hi>worthleſs</hi> Faith of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels,</hi> and the <hi>operative ſaving</hi> Faith of the operation of God. Though the difference be as plain, as that of a <hi>painted Sun</hi> upon a rotten Sign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt, from the <hi>true Sun</hi> in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle Heaven. In a word: Thou muſt diſcourſe thy ſelf ſoundly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning theſe things; and admit no reſt, till thou feeleſt thy ſelf more then <hi>almoſt perſwaded:</hi> Till thou canſt ſay (as the Doctor of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,) I know and am perſwaded;</hi> (and as the Doctor of the <hi>Jews,</hi>) <hi>I believe, and I am ſure;</hi> Lord,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:40387:25"/>
               <q>1. There is a God. 2. This God is Three diſtinct Perſons, as to manner of Being and of Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. 3. Of theſe Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, the Firſt hath eternally <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed;</hi> the Second hath in time dearly <hi>Purchaſed</hi> the Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of loſt Sinners; and this the Third hath convincingly <hi>Proved.</hi> 4. I periſh for ever, if this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation be not Purpoſed <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning</hi> me; if it be not Purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>for me;</hi> and if it be not Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, ſome way, <hi>unto me.</hi> 5. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til I have this Proof made unto me, I cannot poſſibly have know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Purchaſe and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe touching me. 6. Wherefore I <hi>ought,</hi> I <hi>may,</hi> and I <hi>will</hi> by Gods aſſiſtance, ſeek diligently this ſaid Proof unto my inmoſt Heart and Reins!</q> Haſten, <hi>Man,</hi> haſten thou, go Read, go Pray, go Hear, and go Conſult the beſt Miniſters, and Chriſtians: Beſeech them both,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:40387:26"/>to tell thee how they gat aſſurance and certainty hereof; charge them to pray the ſame Spirit, in the uſe of like means, to give it unto thee. But this caution take thou: Never judge thy Belief right and valid, until it diſcover it ſelf to be ſo by theſe properties. <hi>e. g. Till it do ſhame thee for former neglects of the Father, Son, and Spirit; and their Purpoſe, Purchaſe, and Proof.</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thy bluſhing Soul to exclaim; <q>O never had I one thought worth the thinking till now! Miſerable Fool, I have lived like a bruit; as if I had been born in the Field, and bred among the Cattle there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. I abhor my ſelf, and every breath of my paſt Life.</q> Again, <hi>Till it do ſmart and pain thee, and give thee grievous feelings, of thy want of more acquaintance with the Divine Perſons, and theſe their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> Cauſing thee to eſteem and deſire acquaintance with the ſame,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:40387:26"/>above all the ſenſual delights under the Sun. Likewiſe, <hi>Till it become an effectual Goad to quicken thee to the uſe of all means for it, and a Nail alſo to faſten thy Soul unto it.</hi> Driving thee to this concluſion; <hi>q. d.</hi> 
               <q>Whatever I ſhall henceforth propoſe to my ſelf, or proſecute in the World. I will never ſo abſolutely propoſe any thing. Never ſo laboriouſly and inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly purſue any thing, as my acquaintance with the Divine Perſons, and theſe their foreſaid Works. In other things I will be leſs reſolute and more moderate; in this I will be peremptory, and I will ſtrain every Nerve of my Soul.</q> Laſtly, <hi>Till it do ſweeten, and make grateful and pleaſant all thy Religious pains.</hi> At leaſt, as the moſt imperfect certainty that Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen have of Harveſt, doth impart a ſweetneſs unto their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual motions. Till thou canſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:40387:27"/>truly ſay, thus: <q>So much I know of the Divine Perſons. So far I do credit the Holy Spirits Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of their Works. Such Faith I have of both, that what Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and Duties were hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore burthenſome or undelightful, are now become of my chiefeſt joy: And ſuch as I could not live without.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And now, Man, now firſt beats thy Pulſe. This is the firſt <hi>breath</hi> of thy laudable Life. The firſt <hi>ſtep</hi> of thine toward God. The firſt <hi>ſtroke</hi> of reconciling work. This is the firſt hairs breadth thou haſt ſtirred from thy ſelf-ruining Enmity toward the way of Peace. God ſpeed thee onward! For</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Thou muſt Pray and Labour for the actual poſſeſſion, the comfortable perſwaſion, and the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical improvement of Reconciliation unto God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:40387:27"/>
            <p>Thou art now out of doubt, there is a way to get <hi>poſſeſſed</hi> of the Reconciliation <hi>Purpoſed, Purchaſed, Proved.</hi> But can thy <hi>blindneſs,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſiſtedly, find that way? Or, can thy <hi>halting</hi> Soul enter into, and walk in it unaſſiſtedly? Or, if with much ado thou wer't able, wouldſt thou go without infallible <hi>counſel</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible <hi>aid?</hi> And that for want of asking. Or didſt thou never hear of multitudes that periſh in the very <hi>mouth</hi> of their way? Stumbling un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to perdition, at the very threſhold of the door of Salvation.</p>
            <p>I do now ſuppoſe thee to have an <hi>Eye</hi> in thy Head. And if ſo, I no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing queſtion but thou haſt a <hi>Tongue</hi> in thy Head too. <hi>The Eye of Faith, and Mouth of Prayer, were never yet known far aſunder.</hi> And indeed it would be a wonder, if any ſeer of Reconciliation ſhould not be ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way a wreſtler for it. However, wot it well: Divine Authority re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, and Bounty invites and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treats
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:40387:28"/>thee to ſhew that with thy <hi>ſight</hi> of Reconciliation thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived <hi>Praying Lips,</hi> and <hi>Labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Hands,</hi> and a <hi>large Heart,</hi> crav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no leſs then the three things fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid. Of which in their order, hear what follows.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>For the poſſeſſion of Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto God; let Heaven be made to ring with thy Prayers, and let all that ſee thee on Earth be witneſſes of thy pains.</hi> Pray for it; but not out of Gods own way: That would be to <hi>Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme,</hi> not to <hi>Pray.</hi> Pray for it, by Prayer for the grace whereto God hath made the promiſe of it. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance</hi> by which thou art to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorced from the Law of <hi>Sin,</hi> and Covenant of <hi>Works.</hi> And <hi>Faith,</hi> by which thou art to be joyned in the Goſpel-Covenant unto Jeſus Chriſt. Pray, I bid thee; for <hi>thou art no more able, of thy ſelf, to fulfil the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the Goſpel-Covenant then of the Legal.</hi> And Chriſt has no Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to poſſeſs thee of Peace, till
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:40387:28"/>thou doſt anſwer the demand of the Goſpel-Covenant. <hi>The Elect them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> (though they be loved with a Love of good Will from Eternity,) they <hi>lye under the ſentence of wrath, till they conſent unto the Covenant of Grace.</hi> And muſt ſo do. For Chriſt is not ſent to give <hi>Remiſſion</hi> of ſins before <hi>Repentance</hi> of them; <hi>Acts</hi> 5.31. Nor before <hi>Faith on him,</hi> (which is joyning in Marriage-Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant unto him:) <hi>Acts</hi> 10.43. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.21. But Precept, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of good ſucceſs, provoke Men Unreconciled to Pray for Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and Faith; <hi>Acts</hi> 8.22. <hi>Luke</hi> 18.13. &amp;c. Well, But is <hi>Prayer all? By no means. Thy labour is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, Man.</hi> God knows thy Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, and requires no <hi>Price</hi> from thee. The whole thereof he took from Jeſus Chriſt: But thy <hi>Pains</hi> he will not excuſe thee. He calls ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to <hi>recover themſelves out of the ſnare of the Devil:</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.26. That is, by the moſt diligent uſe of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:40387:29"/>the means of their recovery. By the utmoſt <hi>ſtriving</hi> to keep from all things that hinder Recovery and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation: Such as a Man would make to ſtay himſelf, if he were hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying down a Hill that had a Lake of Fire at the foot of it. As alſo by extreameſt <hi>ſtraining</hi> and putting for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to do all required for Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation. For inſtance; go retire thou; and after Divine Help im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plored, ſit down and <hi>reaſon</hi> the Caſe as ſtrongly as thou canſt with thy ſelf. Urge thy own Soul to conſent to the Goſpel-Covenant; as a good Parent would urge a wild and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Child, with the mightieſt Motives it could find. <hi>Pray and intreat</hi> thy ſelf as importunately as thou art a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Beſeech and beg thy own Soul, as a Parent his Childs, to yield unto God. <hi>Charge</hi> and <hi>command</hi> thy ſelf too; adding the moſt frightful <hi>threats</hi> of Vengeance, and ſweeteſt <hi>promiſes</hi> of Grace to drive and draw thy Heart. Diligently <hi>Anſwer every
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:40387:29"/>conſiderable Objection</hi> thou haſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Repentance and Faith. Tell thy ſelf plainly, come what will as to <hi>Eſtate, Name,</hi> and <hi>Friends, &amp;c.</hi> the Covenant of Grace muſt be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, and ſhall. That thou art re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to uſe any violence poſſible, in this caſe, to get Gods Peace. I mean, the moſt conſtraining <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> the moſt intenſe <hi>Deſires,</hi> the moſt fixed <hi>Reſolutions.</hi> As a Father will catch any way a Child falling into the Fire; making nothing at all of breaking its Arm or Leg, ſo he ſave its Life. Briefly, this know; in order to your Reconciliation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, ſuch pains of yours with your ſelves are as ſurely <hi>neceſſary</hi> as they are <hi>poſſible.</hi> And who, I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, can tell me, when ſuch ſelf-la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours were ever <hi>unprofitable.</hi> When I ſhall hear that any Soul is become ſuch a painful Preacher to its ſelf, perſevering in it; I ſhall not ſtick to ſay, it is anſwering the Call of God in my Text. And I ſhall ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:40387:30"/>think, what a Brand ſoever it has been, 'tis one that muſt not lodge for ever in the Fire. <hi>I am not able much to doubt a Mans well-doing, when I know him painful in Soliloquy, and much in fervent Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> ſhut the Book. Go and make thy <hi>God</hi> above, and thy <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> within, and thy <hi>Friends</hi> that be fit, to ſay of thee, <hi>Behold, he Prays!</hi> And behold, he <hi>labours</hi> more abundantly then Hypocrites do, to lay hold of Life. Then return, and read on; and know, that,</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>For the comfortable perſwaſion of thy being Reconciled unto God, thy Life muſt be Prayer, and thy Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure be Labour.</hi> Thou muſt <hi>Pray</hi> without ceaſing, and <hi>Labour</hi> without complaining; thou muſt always <hi>do,</hi> and evermore <hi>delight,</hi> in both. <hi>In the inſtant wherein, thou conſentest un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Goſpel-Covenant, God and thy Soul are Eternal Friends.</hi> The Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall drop down, and fall into its firſt nothingneſs, when that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:40387:30"/>fails. But though thy ſtate be ſo <hi>ſafe,</hi> 'tis a queſtion how long it will be before it will be <hi>ſweet.</hi> Bitterly did <hi>Mary</hi> weep, when Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſtood by her, ſhe not knowing it. Tears filled <hi>Hagars</hi> Eyes, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpairs drew the Blood of her Heart, when the VVell was faſt by her, and ſhe was not aware of it. 'Tis <hi>often</hi> ſo, through their own fault, and <hi>long</hi> ſo, with Gods reconciled ones. They have their Pardon and their <hi>Paſs for Heaven</hi> ſealed in Heaven; but not knowing ſo much, their Conſciences write and ſign their <hi>Mittimus to Hell:</hi> And ſo make the greateſt part of their Breath be ſpent in Sighs. Horrid Robbery! To God of <hi>Praiſe,</hi> to Souls of <hi>Peace,</hi> and of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefulneſs</hi> in the VVorld. O Chriſtian, this remember: <hi>Want of aſſurance made by negligence, is a ſin whoſe name ought to be Legion:</hi> For 'tis a thouſand ſtrong. Be it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſidered.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:40387:31"/>
            <p>How worthy is full perſwaſion of Gods Peace, to be proſecuted by the utmoſt ſtrength of thy Prayer? And conclude upon this; thou haſt no ground to expect that it ſhould be <hi>given</hi> without thy <hi>asking:</hi> Or be <hi>found</hi> without thy <hi>ſeeking.</hi> Yea, or upon <hi>ordinary</hi> asking and ſeeking. Believe it, 'tis the ſweeteſt of Gods Mercies, and the higheſt of the Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours he beſtows under the Sun. And the generation of his Favourites do, all, bear witneſs; the doth not uſe to <hi>give</hi> it, or <hi>continue</hi> it, much leſs <hi>encreaſe</hi> it, and make it <hi>full,</hi> without eſpecial ardency of Supplication, with accuracy of Converſation.
<note place="margin">See Mr. <hi>H. Hickmans</hi> moſt excellent piece of the Believers Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty toward the Spirit.</note> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed theſe, when they meet, he uſeth to honour with it; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6. <hi>David</hi> ſeems to have <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun</hi> his Prayer at Hells door, but to have <hi>ended</hi> it in the very porch of Heaven. And I have heard of ſome, that under tormentive fears, have
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:40387:31"/>gone into their Chambers, lock'd their Doors, and humbly told their God they could not come away un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til he had given them ſome comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſurance of his Love and Peace: And did not come forth without it. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. <hi>ult.</hi> It is to the right or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers of their Converſation, that the Lord promiſeth to ſhew his Salvation; 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6 18, 19. St. <hi>Paul</hi> reckons up a great deal, neceſſary for attaining aſſurance of it. And ſo doth St. <hi>John;</hi> if you conſider together 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 3.19. with 18th <hi>ver.</hi> I appeal to the common ſenſe of all ſound Believers in the World; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther when they are themſelves, they can content themſelves with a bare <hi>poſſibility,</hi> or no more then a <hi>proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility</hi> of being reconciled unto God? Or with ſo much as we call a <hi>Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional certainty:</hi> Which is, when a Man ſets himſelf to Believe and Obey the Goſpel; confident he is Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled if he be ſincere, but doubting whether he be ſo or no: And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:40387:32"/>they do not ordinarily, when they are without it, <hi>Pray more than ordinarily</hi> for aſſurance; double their Watch; and ſet themſelves to a walk more than commonly ſtrict, both for exerciſe of Graces, and performance of Duties; in order to the firſt <hi>gaining</hi> or <hi>regaining</hi> of loſt aſſurance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> Lay to thy Heart my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. Reſt not in the twilight of Uncertainty. Raiſe thy Holy Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition much higher: And take the courſe juſt now foreſaid, to get poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of poſitive Certainty; that thou mayſt ſail to Heaven with full ſails, and have an abundant en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance. Of this, I nothing doubt, but my Text contains Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Oh that I were as ſure thou wouldſt forthwith ſay; <q>Farewel <hi>curſery Prayers,</hi> and <hi>drowſie Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and <hi>Laodicean Religion!</hi> I might have read my Name in the Book of Life long ago, had it not been for you. You, whom now I
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:40387:32"/>baniſh with this ſolemn proteſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred againſt you. I will hence-forth equally dread to do the works of the Devil <hi>furiouſly,</hi> and to do the work of my God <hi>negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently.</hi> The Prayer, Labour, and Life of Faith, do not <hi>Meritoriouſly purchaſe,</hi> but they do moſt <hi>Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly evidence</hi> Eternal Reconciliation. And in theſe <hi>Chariots</hi> will I go mount and aſcend unto the full aſſurance of Hope. VVhich be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done,</q> I adviſe thee next in theſe words,</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>For the practick improvement both of thy Reconciliation, and of thy aſſurance thereof, let thy Prayers and Pains be heaped up, preſſed down, and running over.</hi> O think not that when thou art certified of thy real Peace with God, thy work is done; thy ſtaff may be ſet behind the door; thou haſt no further to go. No, Chriſtian, no: But then when thou canſt ſo eaſily anſwer, <hi>what thou hast received more than others:</hi> Then, then
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:40387:33"/>is the time for thy ſtraining to get as ready thy Anſwer to a ſecond Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion; <hi>What thou doſt more than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers?</hi> What thou doſt more in all manner of Holy Converſation and Godlineſs, more than thoſe that are unaſſured do; and more than thou thy ſelf didſt do, before thou hadſt aſſurance.</p>
            <p>For why, are the Conſolations of God <hi>Goats hair,</hi> and <hi>ſmall things</hi> with thee? Or dreameſt thou, that they be Talents given thee for thy own <hi>Comfort,</hi> and not for <hi>Gods uſe</hi> and <hi>ſpecial ſervice?</hi> Or, tell me plainly; canſt thou thy ſelf take <hi>Comfort</hi> in them, unleſs thy God has <hi>Glory</hi> from them? Or is it poſſible that ſuch a Man as thou, ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have heard of many, that have by non-improvement ſinned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out of Comfort into Torment? Yea, by the negligence of <hi>one Hour,</hi> loſt the aſſurance they had gotten by the hard Prayers and Labours of <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a Year.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:40387:33"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> If thou art an aſſured Chriſtian; if indeed the ſame Spirit that united thee to Chriſt in thy Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual Calling, and <hi>worked</hi> all Grace in thee, hath alſo <hi>witneſſed</hi> that Grace and Salvation unto thee; then, as for thy Life, conſider; <hi>As ſure as God calls Sinners to come in to the holy ſtate; and calls penitent Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers to go on farther and farther in it: So ſurely doth he call aſſured Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers to go faſteſt and farthest in it.</hi> And the more they do know that their <hi>much is forgiven,</hi> the more to Love and Obey him that forgiveth. A Truth denyed by <hi>none,</hi> nor doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>any,</hi> worthy to be remembred by <hi>all,</hi> and of all, by ſuch as I do ſuppoſe thee.</p>
            <p>Certainly, the aſſured Chriſtian oweth God moſt Thanks. I, and God giveth aſſurance to qualifie for Gratitude, and to provoke unto it. Certainly, <hi>The unthankful are num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred with the unholy;</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2. And are unholy, and that moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturally
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:40387:34"/>too: (For naturally we are Thankful even unto our fellow VVorms.) Yea, moſt univerſally al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. For, <hi>Thankfulneſs, is, in a well explained ſenſe, all our Goſpel-Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi> 'Tis the general Duty of the Goſpel, containing and animating all Duties. All, without it, are impure Carcaſſes. <hi>Repentance,</hi> if it be not Thankful, is rather a Legal rack and rage than a Goſpel Repentance. And <hi>Faith,</hi> if it be not a Thankful Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto the Goſpel-Covenant, 'tis no ſaving Conſent. Nor is the <hi>Love of God,</hi> or any Service of him, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per or tolerable, unleſs they be grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. Unleſs done upon this motive, or account; becauſe <hi>Chriſt hath loved us, and given himſelf for us.</hi> As Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal a Preacher in repute, as any among us, hath theſe memorable words; <hi>If we obſcure the Doctrine of Gratitude, we do as bad or worſe than the</hi> Antinomians. But I return.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> If thou beeſt the Man I ſuppoſe; the reconciled and aſſured
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:40387:34"/>Man, I mean; thou art not yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thy buſineſs. Thou art not obeying my <hi>Text.</hi> Thou art not heeding my <hi>Doctrine:</hi> Unleſs thou art engaged in raiſing thy <hi>Prayers</hi> to a higher pitch; and in refining all thy <hi>Ways</hi> to a further degree, then ever before. Unleſs thou art daily thus ſchooling thy ſelf; <q>Come up my Soul, come up, and ſit up higher. Keep not thou at the threſhold, and juſt within the door of Holineſs, and in the lower pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces any of them. Aſcend, aſcend, aſcend in thy aims at Perfection. Aſcend higher in every Prayer and Petition. Aſcend to the utmoſt heights of <hi>incarnate Sanctity.</hi> To theſe 'tis that Gods Trumpet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larums thee. Nor is it for thee <hi>Excuſable</hi> to do that which for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers would be <hi>Laudable.</hi> Thy aſſuredly Reconciled God, will as aſſuredly ſmite thee with his ſharp Chaſtiſements, if thou doſt but as his unaſſured Children do. If
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:40387:35"/>thou Mortifieſt <hi>Corruptions</hi> but as they. Repelleſt <hi>Temptations</hi> but as they. Acteſt <hi>Graces</hi> but as they. Performeſt <hi>Duties</hi> but as they. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proveſt <hi>Comforts</hi> but as they. Bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Troubles</hi> but as they do. O my Soul, thou muſt, and thou ſhalt in <hi>deſign,</hi> in <hi>deſire</hi> and <hi>endeavour,</hi> do no leſs than PERFECT Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Thou ſhalt love them that hate thee. Thou ſhalt ſwim againſt the ſtream of ſinning multitudes. Thou ſhalt have thy Hopes and Fears moſt, upon unſeen Goods and Evils. Thou ſhalt be merciful to others, and ſevere to thy ſelf. Thou ſhalt chuſe <hi>Moſes</hi> his choice; and ſuffer rather than ſin. Thou ſhalt joy in tribulation. Thou ſhalt fall with Gods Friends, rather than riſe with his Enemies. Thou ſhalt, of all thy ſins, ſacrifice thy <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and thy darling own iniquity. Thou ſhalt live on Goſpel-Promiſes. Thou ſhalt ſtill be upon the Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denying ſide. <hi>Thou ſhalt be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:40387:35"/>for all Duty, but keep thy fire for the weightieſt Duties.</hi> Thou ſhalt count leaſt ſins, no little Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Thou ſhalt love thy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provers. Thou ſhalt in every Commandment look to the Firſt.</q> Which being done, it ſweetly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows;</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Thou muſt aſſiduouſly hope for the Glorious Perfection and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of thy Reconcilement unto God in the day of Judgment, and rejoyce in that hope.</hi> And here, know thou firſt, thy buſineſs is not ſo eaſie as thy warm Heart may preſume it. <hi>Hope</hi> and <hi>Joy</hi> are ſweeteſt feelings: And above all, ſuitable unto our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural deſires, and delightful. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, Hope can have no ſurer ground then Gods <hi>Word, Oath,</hi> and <hi>Sign</hi> and <hi>Seal,</hi> or <hi>Sacrament;</hi> and that thy Hope of perfected Reconciliation hath received. Neither can Joy have a more <hi>congruous</hi> and <hi>compleat</hi> Object, then Gods perfect and publiſhed Friendſhip: And this is it thou haſt
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:40387:36"/>to rejoyce in the expectation of. But alas, both <hi>Hope and Joy have enough to do to live in this World.</hi> They appear to many poor Souls, very improper to the beſt ſtate herein: Becauſe the beſt eſtate on the Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Globe, is not as that in Heaven, without <hi>Sin, Sorrow, Fear, Pains, Enemies, Temptations.</hi> No, but it has the Soul burthened with <hi>guilt;</hi> debaſed and vexed with adhering <hi>corruption</hi> and rebelling; cloathed with <hi>infirmities;</hi> aſſaulted with <hi>tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers;</hi> afflicted by the <hi>world;</hi> beſet with <hi>dangers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs I muſt tell thee, ſuch is thy Nature, that thou muſt and wilt hope, and rejoyce in hope of ſomewhat or other. <hi>Corruption</hi> and <hi>Temptation</hi> will make thee do both on wrong Objects; if <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Heavenly Inſpirations</hi> make thee not exerciſe both, on theſe right ones that I name. And, whatever thou imagineſt, <hi>God is more diſhonoured when he is robbed of theſe affections of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:40387:36"/>Hope and Joy, then when he is denyed any others.</hi> And much more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached, when <hi>you</hi> rob him of them, then when <hi>any other</hi> Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of his ſo do. Any unaſſured of his Peace with them, I mean. So great are thy engagements to live hoping, and joying in the hope of thy perfected publiſhed Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Doſt ask me <hi>what Hope is?</hi> I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, It is Deſire; though all Deſire be not Hope. By Hope, I do un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand a Deſire of ſome good that we think <hi>future,</hi> and to come; tho through many difficulties. A Deſire that is <hi>continued</hi> and perſiſted in; not ſuch as a Childs is of its play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things, which is loſt and gone with the next fancy that ſtarts in its mind. A Deſire, that is alſo <hi>exerciſed</hi> in thinking and expecting of its Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; and can no more be ſatisfied without it, than Hunger without Bread. A Deſire, <hi>not eaſily to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted</hi> for ſo much as ſhort ſpaces of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:40387:37"/>time from its object; but cleaving inceſſantly unto it in <hi>Meditations,</hi> and <hi>Suppoſitions</hi> and <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs. In the <hi>Learned Languages,</hi> Hope is expreſſed by words that ſignifie to look out at ſomething diſtant, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it often and wiſtly, and as it were to ſend our Souls out at our Eyes to go meet it. I have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where read, that the <hi>Hungarian</hi> word for <hi>Hope</hi> is <hi>Remeni,</hi> of <hi>Re,</hi> which ſignifies Above, and <hi>Meni</hi> as they call Heaven. Very proper, being that the fully reconciled ſtate there, is indeed the principal object of ſacred Hope: <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.2. <hi>We rejoyce in hope of the Glory of God. Col.</hi> 1.27. <hi>Chriſt in you, the hope of Glory.</hi> To wit, the Glory put on Believers in the great day of their compleated and proclaimed Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation.</p>
            <p>Stay <hi>Reader;</hi> cloſe now thy Eyes, and think what of this Hope is, and what of it ought to be in thee! And, as 'tis no hard thing to do, tell thy
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:40387:37"/>ſelf what a Life a good meaſure of this Hope would make thee; how Serviceable, how Comfortable!</p>
            <p>The latter God requires from thee as ſurely as the former. Where be thy <hi>Eyes</hi> if thou ſeeſt not the expreſs Texts, which the Holy Scripture pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents? Where thy <hi>Reaſon,</hi> if thou conceiteſt that unto ſo full an <hi>object</hi> of Joy given thee, he doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a proportionable <hi>act?</hi> Awake Man, and ſay thou; what is it muſt go to compleat an object for Joy? And of all of it, what one thing is wanting in compleat Friendſhip with thy God. We rejoyce in <hi>things of great value and price.</hi> And ſurely this is a Pearl of price. The Wiſeſt Lord paid the deareſt price for it. We rejoyce in <hi>things proportionable unto our wants.</hi> And this will not leave one unſupplyed, or any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire uncrowned. We rejoyce in <hi>things pure.</hi> And ſurely, if the Sun in the Firmament hath ſpots, this bleſſed Light hath not one. We rejoyce in
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:40387:38"/>
               <hi>things wonderful.</hi> And ſurely this is the greateſt wonder that Infinite Power ever wrought. We rejoyce in <hi>things that preſent varieties.</hi> And ſurely this muſt have abundance in the Rivers of its Pleaſures. We re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in <hi>Victory.</hi> And this is nothing but Eternal Triumph it ſelf. We re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in <hi>Preferment.</hi> And this is the higheſt exaltation that we can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive; yea, and higher than we can conceive. We rejoyce in <hi>excellent Company.</hi> And here all that is Love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is to meet, and never to part.</p>
            <p>And now I ask, what does the Lord thy God require of thee, if not to rejoyce in the hope of this Glory? <hi>Greatly</hi> to rejoyce in it, and <hi>always.</hi> This thou mayſt do, and ſorrow never the leſs, but much the more for thy ſins. <hi>The Feaſt of the Paſſeover admitted bitter Herbs, yea required them.</hi> And many a ſweet ſhower have I ſeen fall, while the Sun has beautifully ſhone. Indeed <hi>perfect Joy</hi> is not to be had on this
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:40387:38"/>ſide of Heaven: But we might, and we ought to ſeek and find <hi>ſufficient Joy.</hi> Sufficient to make our Lives ſweeter than any Sinners be. To make <hi>the things that do embitter our Lives</hi> leſs grievous to us, and more tolerable than they be. To make <hi>vain Recreations</hi> and <hi>Pleaſures falſely called,</hi> more deſpicable to us than they be. To make the <hi>Thoughts of God</hi> and <hi>the Life to come,</hi> more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar and pleaſant than they be. To make <hi>Ordinances,</hi> and publick and private <hi>Duties</hi> more delightful; and the <hi>thoughts of Death</hi> far leſs terrible. I heartily compaſſionate the poor <hi>melancholly</hi> Creatures, (as Men will call them,) who by means of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive <hi>Bodily Maladies,</hi> are incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citated (ſave by Miracle, or Gods ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary working,) to rejoyce as they ought. As to their own Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs, I know the matter is not ſo great as we are prone in our haſt to think. Through thoſe ſaid Maladies, Satans advantaged Malice leads them
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:40387:39"/>eaſily into miſtakes of their ſtate; and makes them breathe in trouble as in their Element, and never know many hours but full of griefs and fears. Nevertheleſs the day of their perfected and publiſhed Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will wipe away all their Tears; and give them Joys enough to drown the memory of their Sorrows in.</p>
            <p>But O Chriſtian, whoever thou art that haſt not <hi>that Milſtone about thy Neck;</hi> that horrid hinderance of high and holy rejoycing; grant me my requeſt. As upon my Knees I beg and pray thee, <hi>make Conſcience of the command to rejoyce and be exceeding glad, in hope of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Reconciliation!</hi> For the <hi>Lords</hi> ſake, for thy <hi>Souls</hi> ſake, for <hi>Saints</hi> ſake whom thy Joy will ſtrengthen, for pity to <hi>Sinners,</hi> whom thy ſour ſad Countenance will harden; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in the hope of thy Glory! <hi>Rejoyce preſently, in proſpect of that wherein thou must rejoyce Eternally!</hi> And without one Minutes ſtop or
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:40387:39"/>ſtay. Dread, and depart as from Hell upon Earth, from all that tends to keep thee from this Heaven upon Earth! <hi>Bucholtzer</hi> knew what he wrote, when his Pen drop'd this word; <hi>Laetari in Deo— A Holy Man is never ſo like a Holy Angel, as when he rejoyces in God.</hi> Have thy ſet times for ſolemn Conſideration of theſe things: <hi>ſc.</hi> How God is <hi>Pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> and <hi>Honoured</hi> by Joy ſo Hallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. How he <hi>Praiſeth</hi> it, and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardeth</hi> it. How much it honours him more than pining querulous Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row doth. How certain it is, that the moſt pious and penitent Sorrow, is nothing but a Purge preſcribed by him for cleanſing us; and making us to reliſh the fat things of the Feaſt that I ſpeak of. How excellently <hi>this Joy ſtrengthens the Soul, ſweetens Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, lightens Trouble, graceth Religion, ſuits the Goſpel, and an adopted ſtate:</hi> Yea, and ſerves to ſubdue the ſins that moſt eaſily beſet us, and moſt extreamly peſter us: Even in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:40387:40"/>more than all the ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſquieting <hi>diſtraction,</hi> that goes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of <hi>Humiliation.</hi> In a word: How deſirable a temper the Apoſtles was, <hi>As ſorrowful, yet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways rejoycing;</hi> 2 Cor. 6.10. <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing alway, yet never as men without hope;</hi> 1. Theſſ. 4.13. <hi>Reader,</hi> I muſt hope, if thou doſt thus, thy following Life ſhall be a perpetual labour for abiding and abounding Joy: And that, if <hi>Bodily Maladies and Satanical Illuſions</hi> have made Grief and Fear a ſecond nature to thee, thou wilt be perſwadable! Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwadable to make ſo neceſſary a rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and try to tear thy ſelf from thy ſelf, for the poſſeſſion of this under Heaven. <hi>The God of Hope fill thee with all Joy and Peace in believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and expecting thy perfected publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Reconciliation! Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My next undertaking, is to <hi>evince the truth</hi> of my Doctrine thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained. To <hi>demonſtrate,</hi> that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man hath this to do, and no Man
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:40387:40"/>hath any more to do in the World; but to believe and conſider Gods <hi>Purpoſe,</hi> Chriſts <hi>Purchaſe,</hi> and the Holy Ghoſts <hi>Proof</hi> of their purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and purchaſed Reconciliation. To Pray and Labour for the <hi>poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> for the <hi>perſwaſion,</hi> and for the <hi>practical improvement</hi> of it: And to Hope, and rejoyce in the Hope of the <hi>perfection</hi> and <hi>publication</hi> of it in the day of Jugment.</p>
            <p>I dare not <hi>decline</hi> it, knowing that many do need it. Nor ſhall I be <hi>prolix</hi> in it. They that cannot ſee by the Light of the <hi>one</hi> Sun in the Firmament, would not ſee if there were a <hi>thouſand</hi> ſhining thence. Their Conviction I deſpair of, whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever theſe three Conſiderations ſhall not convince. But I propoſe them with an humble confidence, that they ſhall be made <hi>Eye-ſalve</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſome Souls: And mighty through God, againſt Infidelity; as very <hi>Spittle and Clay,</hi> as they ſhall appear
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:40387:41"/>in any wanton Eyes. They are but three.</p>
            <p>C. 1. <hi>The ſure word of Propheſie ſets us this to do, and no more.</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the Scripture to be Gods <hi>Word,</hi> and a perfect Revelation of his <hi>Will,</hi> and a compleat Rule of our <hi>Duty;</hi> and you acknowledge the truth of my Doctrine: I am content that no man believe it ever the more for my Miniſtry of it, if I do not ſhew that the Scripture ſets us to do all I ſay: Or if it can be ſhewn that it ſets us any one thing more than I ſay. <hi>Reader,</hi> Rouze up thy Soul, and read not with ordinary care what follows. I will not overwhelm thee with many Texts; but be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to ſet very plain and pertinent ones before thee.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Belief</hi> and <hi>Conſideration</hi> of Gods Love and Gracious <hi>Purpoſe</hi> to Reconcile Sinners, is ſet us: <hi>Pſalm</hi> 130.4. <hi>There are forgiveneſſes with thee, that thou mayſt be feared.</hi> That is; <hi>q. d.</hi> 
               <q>Lord, ſhouldſt thou deal
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:40387:41"/>with the beſt Man alive according unto thy Laws ſtrictneſs, and his own Souls frequent fears; Hell muſt have him. But O, thou haſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal and Unalterable Purpoſes of forgiving Sins, and Reconciling Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners unto thy ſelf. And this is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved and conſidered of, by thy Bleſſed Command. And if it were not, there were no manner of foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for Religion in the World. All our encouragement to all our Worſhip of thee, is taken from this;</q> 
               <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16. <hi>God ſo loved the World that he gave his only begotten Son, that whoſoever believes on him ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting Life.</hi> Who ſees not here the <hi>Fountain</hi> of all good; Gods Love, that is, his Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Will and Purpoſe to Reconcile Sinners. This is ſet to be ſeen and conſidered firſt: Then the <hi>Conduit,</hi> through which all the good muſt flow from that Fountain; even, Chriſt the Purchaſer of purpoſed Reconciliation. Then the <hi>Veſſels,</hi>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:40387:42"/>which muſt receive all good from the Fountain through the Conduit: Namely, Believers on Chriſt, entire Conſenters to be his in the Bond of the Goſpel Covenant. Then the <hi>ſtreams of good,</hi> by thoſe Veſſels to be received through the Conduit from the Fountain: Even Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance from ruining Enmity, and Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of bleſſed Friendſhip with God for ever. To name no more, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. we are commanded <hi>to make our Election ſure.</hi> Our Election paſſively, is Gods actively. <hi>Gods eternal purpoſe to Reconeile us.</hi> But how ſhould this be made ſure unto our hearts, without their believing and conſidering that God has Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Purpoſes about that matter?</p>
            <p>The <hi>Belief</hi> and <hi>Conſideration</hi> of Chriſts <hi>Purchaſe</hi> of Reconcilement, is ſet us: 1 Tim. 1.15. <hi>This is a faithful ſaying, and worthy of all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation, that Christ Jeſus came into the World to ſave ſinners.</hi> 'Tis the true and great Fundamental Article
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:40387:42"/>of Chriſtian Faith. Worthy of all reception into Conſideration and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement; that Chriſt came to ſave Sinners from Enmity, and reconcile them unto God Everlaſtingly; <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.10. <hi>When we were enemies, we were reconciled to God by the death of his Son.</hi> When we did hate and were hated of God, Jeſus Chriſt paid a valuable, or rather invaluable, price, to buy our Reconciliation; and bought it, leaving us as little <hi>need</hi> as we had <hi>ability</hi> to bring any Meritory price for it: And how plainly do all the Texts that command our Faith in Chriſts Blood, whereby it is Purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; ſuppoſe our Belief and Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of it to precede?</p>
            <p>The <hi>Belief</hi> and <hi>Conſideration</hi> of the Holy Ghoſts <hi>proof</hi> of this, is ſet us. That it is, in eſpecial manner, the work of the Glorious Spirit, to Reveal and to Communicate all Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the Father, and all Purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Son, is foreſhewn in this our <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> well known to the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:40387:43"/>
               <hi>Church</hi> of Chriſt; and admirably well ſhewn by him, whom I uſe to call <hi>John the Divine;</hi> I mean, our Learned Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> in his <hi>Pneumato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie,</hi> or <hi>Diſcourſe of the Holy Spirit;</hi> worthy to be wrote in Cedar and Marble. That we are required to believe and to conſider his teſtimony of this matter, this ſingle Text would brightly evince, if we had no other; <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.31. <hi>The blaſphemy againſt the Holy Ghoſt ſhall not be forgiven unto mer.</hi> Obſerve here; our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour had Preached Gods <hi>Purpoſe,</hi> and his Errand into the World to make a <hi>Purchaſe</hi> of the Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sinners. The <hi>Proof</hi> hereof was made by many Teſtimonies of the Holy Ghoſt: Principally by Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles wrought by his Power; which indeed are the utmoſt proofs poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Theſe themſelves, ſome would not believe and conſider unto due purpoſe. No, but as it is <hi>Mar.</hi> 3.30. They ſaid it was an <hi>unclean</hi> or <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true</hi> Spirit that Chriſt had to witneſs
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:40387:43"/>theſe things. And this their Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous Unbelief and Inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, is declared unpardonable; even ſo, as no other ſin is.</p>
            <p>Reader, Canſt thou think of this without horrour? But ſee alſo, how are we warned not to <hi>reſiſt,</hi> not to <hi>quench,</hi> not to <hi>grieve</hi> the Holy Spirit. <hi>Acts</hi> 7.51. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.30. Not to <hi>reſiſt</hi> him in the Ordinances of his Word, teſtifying unto us Gods foreſaid Purpoſe, and Chriſts Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, in order to draw us to a due purſuit of our Reconcilement. Not to <hi>grieve</hi> him; that is, not to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke him to leave us, as our Friends uſe to do when we offend them; by Unbelief and Inconſideracy of his foreſaid Teſtimony. Not to <hi>quench</hi> him; that is, not to oppoſe and put out the Light and Evidence he giveth us of the things foreſaid; preferring our Darkneſs above his Light; chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing rather to be ignorant than to know Gods <hi>Purpoſe,</hi> and Chriſts <hi>Purchaſe</hi> of the ſaid Reconciliation.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:40387:44"/>
               <hi>Not to Believe and to Conſider the Holy Spirits foreſaid Proof, is to Reſiſt, and Quench and Grieve him; if any thing be ſo to do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Labour</hi> for the <hi>poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion</hi> of this reconciliation is ſet us. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.28. <hi>Repent</hi> (ſaith <hi>Peter</hi> to <hi>Simon Magus) and pray God, if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the thought of thine heart may be forgiven thee.</hi> That is, Pray, if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly thou mayeſt get poſſeſt of God's Peace and reconciliation. <hi>Luke</hi> 13, 24. <hi>Strive to enter in at the ſtrait gate, for many I ſay unto ye, will ſeek to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in and will not be able.</hi> That is, do your utmoſt to enter into the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſtate, to get joyned to the Lord in the Goſpel-Covenant of reconcil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Grace, For many faint, chill, luke-warm ſouls will ſeek, but inef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually. But put ye your utmoſt power into act.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prayer,</hi> and <hi>Labour</hi> for the certain <hi>perſwaſion</hi> of this reconciliation is ſet us. Prayer, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4, 6. <hi>Lord lift thou up the light of thy Countenance on
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:40387:44"/>us. David</hi>'s example is obliging in this caſe. Labour; 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren give diligence to make your Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling (that is,</hi> into the ſtate of recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation with God;) and <hi>Election ſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Labour</hi> for the <hi>practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal improvement</hi> of this reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ſet us. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.65, 66. <hi>Thou hast dealt well with thy Servant, O Lord:</hi> (and what follows?) <hi>Teach me good Judgment and Knowledge.</hi> That is, holily to improve thy love. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.32. compare with <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.1. <hi>God for Chriſt's ſake hath forgiven you;</hi> or been reconciled to you. And what then is inferred? <hi>Be ye therefore fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers,</hi> or (as in the Original) <hi>Imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of God, as dear Children.</hi> That is, as thoſe that think they can never do enough to expreſs their Love and Thankfulneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hope,</hi> and <hi>Joy in the Hope,</hi> of the <hi>perfection</hi> and <hi>publication</hi> of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation to God, in the day of Judgment, is alſo ſet us. Hope, <hi>Tit.</hi>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:40387:45"/>2, 11, 12, 13. <hi>The Grace of God that bringeth Salvation, teaches us to deny ungodlineſs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and live ſoberly, righteouſly and godly in this preſent World. Looking for that bleſſed Hope, and the glorious appearing of the great God and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Joy <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Rejoyce in the Lord, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. And again I ſay, Rejoyce.</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5, 16. <hi>Rejoyce evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude, He that doth theſe things, is certainly <hi>acceptable unto God, and approved of Men.</hi> All, that do fear God. Nor can any an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer be made to his ſhame, if ſuch a one ask, <hi>What lack I yet?</hi> If any do dream otherwiſe; and ſear that this is not the whole Duty of man; let them ſhew but one thing more, and I will bear the ſhame.</p>
            <p>C. 2. <hi>The Nature of Religion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires this, and no more.</hi> I muſt be underſtood of <hi>Poſtlapſarian</hi> Religion. Religion as ſince Man's Fall it has been modelled. Be it conſidered that Religion, as ſo conſidered, is
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:40387:45"/>nothing elſe but a <hi>reſtored Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, or a Reconciliation between God and Man,</hi> And this made in a way preſcribed by the VViſdom and VVill of God whoſe revealed VVill, is to deal with man in a way agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the <hi>Nature</hi> whereof he hath made him; and yet in every reſpect ſuited to the <hi>Soveraignty</hi> he hath over him. Plainly thus; in all his wayes with us, God will himſelf ſo act, that the Power and Praiſe ſhall be as <hi>viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly</hi> as <hi>truly</hi> his own. Yet ſo, that there ſhall be room and place for our acting <hi>by</hi> and <hi>under</hi> him. And Duty ſhall ſtill be <hi>truly</hi> and <hi>viſibly</hi> ours.</p>
            <p>In this Reconciliation, each per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the bleſſed Trinity hath his Gracious Part. <hi>The Father Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciles us,</hi> to wit as the <hi>Primary Cauſe,</hi> purpoſing of it, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. <hi>The Son Reconciles us;</hi> to wit as the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious</hi> Purchaſer; <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.16. <hi>The Bleſſed Spirit Reconciles us;</hi> as the <hi>Efficient</hi> VVorker and VVitneſſer of the Grace, by which we are made
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:40387:46"/>Partakers of the Reconciliation, and are aſſured thereof, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3, 5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.5. So that the <hi>Kingdom, Power,</hi> and <hi>Glory,</hi> is here illuſtriouſly and equally to be aſcribed unto the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son</hi> and <hi>Spirit.</hi> In the mean time, we alſo have our part left us. <hi>We are bid, in my Text, our ſelves to Reconcile our ſelves.</hi> That is, to do our part toward it. So <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.11. <hi>Turn ye, turn ye;</hi> that is, Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile, Reconcile your ſelves; <hi>q.d.</hi> No longer turn your backs on God, as Enemies; turn about your Faces to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward him as Friends.</p>
            <p>Now, what I affirm is this. Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that <hi>this part to be done by us to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward our Reconciliation, conſiſts in the things foreſaid and no more.</hi> Of theſe we are capable by the aids of Divine Grace. And ſo proper are all theſe to be done by us, that the Neglect muſt needs incenſe Divine Juſtice. Of doing ought more, we have no <hi>Capacity;</hi> (as bleſſed be God,) we have no <hi>Commandment</hi> in his Word,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:40387:46"/>which hath been fore-aſſerted.</p>
            <p>Of <hi>Believing</hi> and <hi>Conſidering</hi> the parts done by the Divine Perſons, we have Capacity. <hi>Natural,</hi> I mean. Though <hi>impotent</hi> and <hi>perverſe</hi> our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties be, till Grace give them <hi>ſtrength</hi> and <hi>inclination</hi> unto good. They were created in us by God for this Noble uſe. And ſhould he admit our Reconciliation without their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing uſed thereto, an unſufferable ſpot would fall upon his infinite <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi> It would be ſaid; he had made noble Powers, for no uſe, or but vile. Yea, and upon his <hi>Truth</hi> alſo. For it would be ſaid, <hi>His wrath came not down upon the very children of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief.</hi> Contrary to <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>Of <hi>Praying</hi> and <hi>Labouring</hi> for our Poſſeſſion, Perſwaſion, and Practick improvement of Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation unto God, the ſame is to be ſaid. We have <hi>Natural,</hi> and ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Engliſh</hi> people may be ſuppoſed to have ſome <hi>Acquired Abilities</hi> too. If not <hi>gracious and ſupernatural.</hi> And
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:40387:47"/>alas, what did God give us theſe for? What a Blemiſh would it be unto his <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> if he ſhould require no uſe of them unto their chiefeſt ends. But grant us <hi>Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation,</hi> and <hi>Aſſurance,</hi> and <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Proſperity</hi> without them. And let it be told through the Earth, that he was <hi>no Condemner of ſlothful ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</hi> Nor <hi>Enemy to ſuch as call not upon his name.</hi> He bids us pray and labor for Spirituals; he forbids us to Crave and Cark for Temporals. O how ſhould he then make us plow and ſow for Temporals, and not make us pluck our hands out of our Boſomes for Spirituals.</p>
            <p>Of <hi>Hoping,</hi> and <hi>Rejoycing in Hope</hi> of compleat Reconciliation, the ſelf-ſame, is plainly ſeen. How full is our <hi>Nature</hi> of Love, Hope, and Joy? How <hi>Noble Affections</hi> are they, and pleaſant? And for what were they put into us? Very Children need little Information. And very Blind they are, that ſee not how ill
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:40387:47"/>it would reflect upon their <hi>Author,</hi> ſhould he require no uſe of ſuch <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents.</hi> And ſhould he endure his Friends by the diſuſe of theſe, to publiſh contempt of his Friendſhip. For 'tis a publick Declaration that we have made us <hi>another God,</hi> when our Love doth not exerciſe it ſelf in Hope and Joy toward the <hi>true.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereof it is, more than this, that we poor Creatures are capable, I proclaim my extreme ignorance. <hi>Graces</hi> all, and <hi>Worſhip</hi> Natural and Inſtituted, and <hi>Duties</hi> (perſonal and relative) are plainly enough com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended. Nor may I beſtow time to light Candles in that Sun. Laſtly,</p>
            <p>C. 3. <hi>The whole Generation of the Religious will vouch it, that their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſtands in this, and no more.</hi> No more, unto any of them known. Next to the Infallible Scriptures, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend me to the <hi>common ſenſe of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers,</hi> for the reſolution of a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Caſe. <hi>Reader,</hi> go try a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the beſt known unto thee.</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:40387:48"/>
            <p>Ask them ſeriouſly two things.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) <hi>Whether they do or dare in iheir daily walk, to let fall any one of the particulars aforeſaid? ſc.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief and Conſideracy of the <hi>Purpoſe, Purchaſe,</hi> and <hi>Proof</hi> of Reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation unto God. Prayer, and Labor for the <hi>Poſſeſſion, Perſwaſion, Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical Improvement.</hi> Hope and Joy in the hope of its final Glorious <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pletement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">(2.) <hi>What other Religious Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes they have, then of Faith with Meditation, Prayer with painfulneſs of Means for things pray'd fer, Hope with Joy?</hi> Upon me be the ſhame, if any other be found. And if thou beeſt not told by all; that if theſe Exerciſes do pleaſe thee, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in Chriſtian Religion to offend thee. <hi>Bleſſed is the Man whoſoever is not offended in one of theſe! And who confines his Care only unto theſe.</hi> The <hi>Italians</hi> have a ſaying, <hi>Dangerous is the man that has but one Buſineſs to do.</hi> But my God and the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:40387:48"/>God of my Fathers grant, that I and my deareſt Friends may never have more to do than one. And that one, be our Reconciliation unto him!</p>
            <p>Of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of this Doctrine, the one half cannot be told you within the ſpace of a Sermon. And of that which might be, I ſhall wave much, to preſs that which (I think) is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed moſt. Come <hi>Reader,</hi> and let me gain thy <hi>Attention</hi> to it, and win thy <hi>Heart</hi> by it. Read, and every two or three Lines thou readeſt, Lift up thy Soul to Heaven. And <hi>put thy name into the number of the Reconciled,</hi> now at this very Sermon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Is Reconciliation unto God, the Duty, and whole Duty of every Man?</hi> Believeſt thou this? Thou wilt then (among many others) make theſe Inferences.</p>
            <p>Inf. 1. <hi>God and Men, are not as God and Divels, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreconcilable.</hi> It is true, they are much the ſame as to <hi>certain Enmity. An unconvert man is is truly at Enmity with God, as any
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:40387:49"/>damned Angel is.</hi> They are alſo very like, as to the exceeding Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of Reconciliation. <hi>As much is to be done to reconcile God and an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convert Soul, as would be neceſſary to do to reconcile God and Beelzebub.</hi> As great a <hi>price</hi> muſt be paid unto God for the one as the other. As great a <hi>Change</hi> muſt be wrought in the one as in the other. And as great a <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer</hi> muſt go to the working of the Change in one, as in the other. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, though we are like <hi>Camels,</hi> with like <hi>Bunches on our Back;</hi> there is no compariſon between us and them, as to poſſibility of paſſing through the <hi>Needles Eye.</hi> Infinite <hi>Power,</hi> to which all things are poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and <hi>equal Goodneſs,</hi> that ſhews it ſelf in things wonderful, hath made a wide difference. <hi>The Condition of Devils is not more truly deſperate, than the Condition of Men is hopeful. And of any men, the Condition of thoſe whom God is preſſing and ever praying to be reconciled unto him.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:40387:49"/>
            <p>The Reconciliation of Divels is <hi>impoſſible;</hi> but the Reconciliation of ſuch Men, is <hi>more than poſſible;</hi> even <hi>probable.</hi> On <hi>Gods part,</hi> probable; for he is at work for it. And upon <hi>Mens own part,</hi> probable; for they are, or appear to be, at work for it alſo. <hi>Reader,</hi> I beſeech thee by the tender Mercies of God, through which this is true and plain, fix well this great Truth on thy Soul. I am a Man that have ſomewhat to do with many poor dubious Souls. Of moſt that come to me, I do plainly ſee this: It hath been unbelief of this truth, that hath long kept them from ſeeking after God. It is unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of it, that now fills them with fears inordinate in ſeeking after him; and makes them come crying to me day after day, <hi>No hope, no hope.</hi> To the trouble of my <hi>ſoul,</hi> and no ſmall expence of my <hi>time.</hi> But I forbear. Let me add this only more; although his Truth <hi>ſeem</hi> to be Believed by all bold Sinners among us, it doth <hi>but
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:40387:50"/>ſeem</hi> ſo. All indeed do <hi>grant</hi> it, but very few do <hi>believe</hi> it. And of them that do, this muſt be ſaid; their <hi>Belief</hi> is a corrupt one, and its <hi>Fruits</hi> are moſt abominable. <hi>'Tis ſo that they believe God to be Reconciled, as hence to be made Fear him much the leſs, but Love him, and ſeek his Peace never the more.</hi> Could ſuch <hi>Fruit</hi> riſe from the <hi>Root</hi> of an intelligent and ſound Faith? It could not. Briefly, let me tell thee, that this Truth is moſt fundamental: And Disbelief of it is extream Blaſphemy, againſt the <hi>Truth, Holineſs,</hi> and <hi>Faithfulneſs</hi> of the moſt high God. It is true; ſuch as have ſinned the ſin againſt the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, have the door of Mercy ſhut upon them for ever. But to me it appears as true; that, who ſuch Perſons be, is known unto God on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: Not diſcovered unto themſelves or any other Men. <hi>I tell the worst Sinners that come to hear me, They have as much ground to hope that God will accept them if they do Convert, as
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:40387:50"/>ever</hi> Abraham, Iſaac, <hi>or</hi> Jacob <hi>had, before they did Convert.</hi> Yea, and becauſe of our Goſpel Sun-ſhine, more then they had.</p>
            <p>I. 2. <hi>Love indeed runs downward: And incomparably greater is the Love of God to Man, then the Love of Man unto God, or unto himſelf.</hi> This I gather from Gods beginning the <hi>Peace,</hi> though Man began the <hi>Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel.</hi> From his here ſo calling on us to accept it; as ſpeaks his <hi>forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> to give, and our <hi>backwardneſs</hi> to receive it. From his amazing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcention even to pray and beſeech us to receive it. This Love is as much above that of Earthly Parents, as the Heavens are above the Center of the Earth. But what is our Love of God, what is our Love of our ſelves? I know not a greater lover of his God, in all this World, then the Man that printeth theſe words: <hi>My God knoweth that I even abhor and loath my ſelf, becauſe I love and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in him no more.</hi> And in another
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:40387:51"/>place: <hi>I can more eaſily forgive my ſelf all my other ſins, then my loving God ſo little.</hi> O what muſt others ſay? Other <hi>Saints,</hi> I mean, of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour ſtature unto him. And for <hi>Sinners,</hi> that make light of all Gods Calls to Reconciliation; and are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexible by his very intreaties, for whole <hi>Weeks, Months,</hi> and <hi>Years</hi> together; who ſees it not? <hi>Their Life is a practical proteſt, that they will bear the priſon of Hell, the torment of Fire, and that for the ſpace of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, rather than be friends with God.</hi> So they love God; ſo they love them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. 'Tis true, we cannot here perſwade them, but that they do truly love themſelves, and their God too. But <hi>in utter darkneſs it ſelf men will ſee better.</hi> There they will ſee and ſay, God was kind, and made them good offers; but they were themſelves their own deſtroyers; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by ſin bewitch'd, in <hi>heart</hi> to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him, and in <hi>act</hi> to murder them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. There they will underſtand
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:40387:51"/>the <hi>ſenſe,</hi> as well as feel the <hi>truth,</hi> of <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.36. and 35.</p>
            <p>There they will know to their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, what it is for God to beſeech and pray ſinful Duſt to come take Pardon and Peace; and for them to lend him a <hi>deaf ear,</hi> or give him a more <hi>reproachful repulſe</hi> againſt convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Conſcience. <hi>Reader,</hi> here ſtay a while: Think, and ſpeak with thy ſelf of the huge imports of this word: <hi>[As though God did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you by us.]</hi> How, GOD be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech? SOVERAIGNTY beg? And that of both Creatures and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels too? What meaneth this, and what is it we are to learn by it? <hi>God beſeech!</hi> The word aſtoniſhes me; and filleth my mind with theſe thoughts above others. Firſt, <hi>How pawerful is Love, that makes Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence ſtoop?</hi> Secondly, <hi>How Loveful is the Divine Majeſty, that thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcendeth?</hi> Thirdly, <hi>How wonderful is this condeſcention, whereunto God never ſtooped before, and beyond which
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:40387:52"/>it is not to be thought poſſible that he ſhould ever ſtoop?</hi> Fallen <hi>Angels,</hi> had nothing <hi>like it:</hi> Fallen <hi>Men,</hi> can have nothing <hi>beyond it.</hi> God <hi>ſtoops;</hi> he ſtoops <hi>low;</hi> he ſtoops <hi>his lowest,</hi> unto us. The loweſt that the nature and honour of his Government will admit. <hi>God beſeech!</hi> I do believe; <hi>Lord, help my unbelief.</hi> I do believe, methinks I do ſee, and hear the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly King, even thus addreſſing to his rebellious Subjects: <q>
                  <hi>Miſerable Creatures,</hi> as I made you not miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, I am not pleaſed to ſee you ſo. I have made a <hi>costly proviſion</hi> for your reſtoration to the Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs I made you in: And left you nothing to do for the ſame, but to <hi>accept</hi> it in the way of my <hi>Goſpel-Covenant.</hi> I have <hi>taught</hi> you ſo to accept it. I have <hi>commanded</hi> you, and on no ſmall penalty. And fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, I do <hi>beſeech</hi> and <hi>pray</hi> you, Sirs, <hi>if ye love me,</hi> accept of it. If ye do not love your own Souls, yet <hi>for my ſake</hi> accept it. I will
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:40387:52"/>take it as the greateſt kindneſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my ſelf, and will reward you as though ye had profited me, if ye accept it. You give me my high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt pleaſure if ye accept it. I will ſet <hi>Heaven</hi> ringing for joy thereof if ye accept it. As long as I live, (and my Immortality will not dye in haſt) I will remember and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite you, if ye will accept it. If ye would not do your utmoſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me and your ſelves, ye muſt accept it. If Grief could poſſibly ſieze on Godhead, ye would make me drown Heaven with my Tears if ye did not accept it: And to repent that ever I made you. So good a will do I truly bear you, though Satan and your ſilly Hearts, by him ſeduced, tell you contrary ſtories! Arguing wildly, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I drag you not to <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> againſt your wills, therefore I have not any will that you ſhould have either.</q> 
               <hi>Reader;</hi> again and again read this, and ceaſe not till thy
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:40387:53"/>aſtoniſhed and trembling Soul take fire, and flame forth in exclamations, <hi>What manner of Love is this? Stay me, I am ſick of Love! The Love of God and Chriſt do conſtrain me! O Lord, I am thy ſervant, I am thy Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel Covenant ſervant! I am thine, Lord, ſave me!</hi> In great Letters I wiſh this Truth written upon thy Doors and Walls: <hi>God delighteth more in Reconciling one penitent poor ſinner, than in Damning all the obſtinate World.</hi> I, and the main revenue of his Crown lies in it: Elſe he would not love Mercy above Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice. Nor could we holily deſire to be ſaved.</p>
            <p>Reader, I cannot yet have done with thee. I muſt ſay to thee, as <hi>Ruth</hi> to her Mother in Law, <hi>Intreat me not to leave thee, or return from following after thee with this Inference.</hi> I muſt inſiſt a little more upon Gods ſo aſtoniſhing Intreaty. And I would to God I could <hi>find</hi> or <hi>make</hi> words, prevalent with thee to inſiſt much
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:40387:53"/>hereon. To be often muſing what it is, that <hi>Gods intreaty of ſinners to be reconciled,</hi> doth in good ſober Truth import. I beſeech thee go and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult <hi>God himſelf</hi> in holy Prayer unto him. Go conſult his <hi>Miniſters,</hi> the beſt of them; and ſuch through whoſe Mouths he is moſt likely to ſpeak his Heart unto thee. Go con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, and take advice, whether it import not thus much: To wit, a <hi>real will</hi> of God without any deſign or unſincerity, to have ſinners re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled unto him; even as many of them as he ſends his Goſpel unto. <hi>A will of complacence,</hi> as of a thing that would be highly grateful unto him; though not a <hi>Will efficacious,</hi> and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective of it againſt all wilful and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected unfitneſs in ſinners; ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>added unto their natural. <hi>A Will, that indeed doth not ſo overpower all things, as to bring all ſinners unto Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but yet one that leaves nothing but their own obſtinate Wills to keep them from it.</hi> And makes, that all
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:40387:54"/>who live under the Goſpel, and who do ſeek it as they are directed by the Goſpel, may reaſonably judge their obtainment of it <hi>most highly probable;</hi> and conclude that if their labour for it be loſt, it will not be through failure on Gods part, but their own.</p>
            <p>'Tis very certain, that ſuch influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of the Holy Spirit were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated under the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> that of all that lived and dyed then unreconciled unto God, the fault was laid at their own doors. <hi>Thou gavest thy good Spirit to inſtruct them.</hi> Neh. 9.20. <hi>Turn ye at my reproof, behold I will pour my ſpirit to you, I will make known my words unto you.</hi> Prov. 1.23. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> O how much more muſt we now conclude in the Goſpel day, that <hi>Mens deſtruction is of themſelves?</hi> That the Holy Spirit is always ſtriving with ſinners, and perſwading them to be reconciled, until they do by very great provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations cauſe him to withdraw for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver from them.</p>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:40387:54"/>
            <p>By the <hi>Prophets</hi> of old, the Holy Ghoſt never ſpake in the wondrouſly condeſcenſive Language, which he uſeth in the <hi>New Teſtament.</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in flows the Language of incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable tenderneſs; and ſuch as put it beyond the moſt jealous ſuſpicion, that God is deſirous of our Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the ſaid Reconciliation. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>the Majesty of Heaven even courts every vile Worm of us.</hi> And in moſt compaſſionate manner, aſſays to melt and overcome the perverſeſt ſinner: Even thy ſelf, my Reader, thy ſelf in particular.</p>
            <p>Stay therefore thy ſelf, and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and bleſs. Throw aſide my Book, and go ſhut thee into thy Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet: And there with humble affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate and thankful ſenſe of this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Love, fall on thy Knees and ſay to this purpoſe: <q>
                  <hi>Bleſſed God,</hi> thy works are in themſelves convincing Arguments of thy good Will unto Men. Thy innumerable <hi>Benefits</hi> conferred upon us. Thy Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:40387:55"/>
                  <hi>Judgments,</hi> which in their own nature and in thy deſign are Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinal and wholeſome. The <hi>Time</hi> thou alloweſt us in this <hi>World</hi> and in thy <hi>Church;</hi> which we cannot juſtly take for a meer <hi>reprieve from torment,</hi> but for a <hi>ſpace to Repent in,</hi> and to ſue out our Pardon. Above all, thy giving thy <hi>Son</hi> to dye for our Reconciliation; and thy <hi>Spirit</hi> to inſtruct and perſwade us to be Reconciled. After all, it has ſeemed thee good, to treat us in words of as wonderful Love as that which ſhines in thy works. Words of <hi>Obſecration</hi> and <hi>Intreaty.</hi> Such as the Potſheards of the Earth cannot afford unto their <hi>Inferiours</hi> very often; no, nor unto their <hi>Equals;</hi> nor always unto very <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours.</hi> Thou, great <hi>Judge of the whole Earth,</hi> beſeecheſt Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors moſt worthy of Hell, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept their Pardon! And intreateſt them to endure thee to ſave and glorifie them! This thy <hi>Holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:40387:55"/>admire; at this the <hi>Divels</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy: But I, Lord, I, a <hi>prodigy of ſtupidity,</hi> what do I do? Of a truth I deſire to Praiſe and to Wonder! From this Minute unto Eternal Ages, uninterruptedly to Wonder and Praiſe. I am fully convinced how juſtly I periſh, if indeed I periſh after all this ſo ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perabundant Grace. This thy Love, and thy I know not what, that is more then Love it ſelf, if more can be, doth ſweeten my thoughts of thee. Never was my <hi>Natural Fear</hi> of thee ſo conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, never my <hi>Diabolical Enmity</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee ſo quenched, as now (I truſt) they are. <hi>I am leſs a Divel, ſince I conſidered this thy Love, O my God!</hi> Experience hath now aſſured me, Love begets Love, as Fire kindles Fire!</q>
            </p>
            <p>I. 3. <hi>Mans Enmity unto God, tho' it be ſtrange, tis true.</hi> How elſe could Reconciliation be his Duty, if his ſtate were not of Enmity? It is
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:40387:56"/>confeſſed, <hi>Enmity unto God is a ſtrange thing.</hi> He is <hi>all</hi> Good, and nothing but Good. Our Nature rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, can Love nothing but what appears Good; and muſt and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but Love all that ſo appears. Unto all Men, if their Profeſſions may be believed, God doth appear as he is now ſaid to be: All, and only, Good. Whence then ſhould Hatred ariſe? To be ſure, unto <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> and <hi>Men,</hi> in their firſt holy ſtate of <hi>Creation,</hi> God did ſo appear, and was verily and undoubtedly ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved. O how could they ever break with God? The particular manner is more <hi>curiouſly</hi> then <hi>profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably</hi> diſputed by Men of argute wits. It is very plain unto all thinking minds, that Creatures, <hi>as ſuch,</hi> are mutable things and defectible. That continuation in any good, is from the <hi>gift</hi> of the Creators Grace; not from the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of the Creatures Nature. That God gave Angels and Men at firſt, a ſtock of Holy Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:40387:56"/>to trade with; and held both <hi>Probationers,</hi> on tryal of their Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs. Some of the Angels, and our Father <hi>Adam,</hi> (the infallible word aſſures us,) prov'd unfaithful. Acted not up to what they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived: Thereby forfeited, and loſt all; all their foreſaid Qualities of <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs;</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, became full of <hi>Folly</hi> and <hi>Malice.</hi> For, as where Light and Heat depart, Darkneſs and Cold muſt enter: Where Wiſdom and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs do ceaſe, Folly and Malice muſt begin to have place. Now hence 'tis, that ever ſince that fatal forfeiture, Devils, and all unrenewed Men, do do nothing but monſtrouſly. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but with monſtrous Folly and Malice. Their Fall made them Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; and <hi>all things must neceſſarily (when they are not overpowered;) act according to their Natures;</hi> let them be what they will. Their depraved Natures, both of them, do carry them to things moſt unnatural. To
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:40387:57"/>things that are, and that they know to be, moſt infinitely <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonable</hi> in themſelves, and <hi>Injurious</hi> unto them. As for example, this of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of God. Men do <hi>much</hi> know, and Divels do <hi>more</hi> know, he is all Goodneſs; and worthy of all Love. That to hate him, is to do the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt hurt to themſelves; and that for which they have not the leaſt cauſe from him; but through the Folly and Malice that Divels hold <hi>remedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly,</hi> and unrenewed Men hold <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,</hi> againſt all Divine Remedies; this is moſt natural unto them. As natural, as for a poyſonous <hi>Fountain</hi> to ſend forth poyſonous <hi>Streams.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And alas, how full is this World of this hatred of God, which few in the World, if any, will own? How leſs full is the Sea of water, then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate <hi>Souls</hi> are full of it? Yea, and their <hi>mouths</hi> and <hi>hands</hi> full of it. Only Divels, be fuller of it than Men: By which means it is, that <hi>on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Hell is worſe then this World we live
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:40387:57"/>in.</hi> We ſee Mens <hi>Hands</hi> at work a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God; we hear their <hi>Tongues</hi> running againſt him in every place; we diſcern hereby what the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of their <hi>Hearts</hi> is againſt him. How paſſionately they wiſh an end put unto his Being. We Inſtruct, Perſwade, Intreat with tears, and Beg them to let us endeavour their recovery to a better mind: Nor is it above <hi>one of a hundred</hi> will regard what we ſay. And yet muſt we be afraid, (if we will be pleaſers of Men,) to tell them they hate God?</p>
            <p>But here I publiſh it: <hi>If I ever ſaw the Sun ſhine, or the Fire burn, or the Water flow, I do ſee all unconvert Men, Women and Children, hate the Bleſſed God.</hi> And whereas, none that I meet with or hear of, do deny but that they are ſinners, and do ſin daily; I aſſure them this is the ſoul and life of their ſin. And were this hatred of God but once expelled, they would no longer be ſinners. Were that but <hi>mortifyed</hi> they would
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:40387:58"/>not be a minute longer <hi>impenitent, or unpardoned ſinners. 'Tis predominant hatred of God, that is the ruine of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry damned Man!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I. 4. <hi>The Goſpel is a Jewel.</hi> This I do argue from our common prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple; that it is the only <hi>directory</hi> and <hi>mean</hi> of our Reconciliation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God. If it be ſo; and if Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation be our only Duty, it is ſurely <hi>ineſtimable.</hi> It can be no leſs I trow, whatever is the divinely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed mean of our whole ſaving Duty. Whatever is, as the Goſpel is, and is named <hi>the Word of Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation.</hi> That, whereby the way of making Peace with God is reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; that which is the very <hi>Charter</hi> and <hi>Grant</hi> of Chriſt, the Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker, and all his benefits, unto every one that will receive it. If my Doctrine be true, the Bleſſed Goſpel deſerves a higher rate, then the beſt of us all appear to put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it.</p>
            <p>Conſider it as an <hi>Hiſtory;</hi> 'tis one
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:40387:58"/>the Angels, unto whom 'tis but a Hiſtory, delight to pry into. As an <hi>offer of Salvation,</hi> 'tis tidings of great, even all, Joy. As a <hi>Rule of Life,</hi> 'tis a Royal Law of Liberty. The <hi>truth</hi> of it, is ſealed by unparallell'd Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. The <hi>Grace</hi> of it, is it ſelf the Miracle of Miracles. In the miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble parts of the World where this Goſpel ſhines not, 'tis ever Night. <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> poſſeſs them. Forlorn Souls (as one ſpeaks,) are there under a continual <hi>Maſſacre;</hi> and be an eaſie <hi>conqueſt</hi> and <hi>prey</hi> to to the Fiends of Hell. But the Places which the Goſpel viſits, (in our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours Language,) are ſaid to be <hi>Lift up unto Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They are found like the World at firſt, a <hi>Tohu</hi> and <hi>Bohu;</hi> but are made by the Goſpel, divine <hi>Temples.</hi> Of Stones, Children are raiſed up unto <hi>Abraham,</hi> by the Goſpel. What was our <hi>England</hi> but a howling <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs,</hi> till the Goſpel made it a <hi>Garden,</hi> and the <hi>Paradiſe</hi> of the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:40387:59"/>Earth. Both for Heavenly and Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly good things. Indeed, all the World is <hi>Egypt;</hi> and <hi>there is no Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhen but of the Goſpels making!</hi> No o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Star, ever led a Soul to it's Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour. The Law damns all; and ſingle Natural Religion ſaves none. The Goſpel is like to the <hi>Archangels Trumpet;</hi> by it Graves are made to open, and dead Souls to come forth. And <hi>the Maſters of moſt refined Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality</hi> will one day find, there is no other Miniſtration of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>Are therefore tears of very Blood, ſufficient to Lament our Goſpel-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. Contempt every where ſhewn; in <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>London</hi> it ſelf, every where. In <hi>Houſes,</hi> where Bibles lie about as neglected, as old Shoes. In <hi>Churches,</hi> where uſually is leſs crowding and earneſt liſtning, than in <hi>Satan's Temples,</hi> our Playhouſes. I would I might not add, in very <hi>Pulpits</hi> too; from whence too often ſoundeth a but <hi>Natural,</hi> and <hi>Legal</hi> Religion, with few, if any <hi>Evangelical</hi>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:40387:59"/>Note in it. It is too truly ſaid, I fear, that many Preach <hi>Adam, Moſes,</hi> and at moſt <hi>John Baptist.</hi> Having little to ſay of <hi>Jeſus Christ;</hi> or of that Reconciliation by him through the Goſpel-Covenant, which they ſeem to think that their People <hi>have</hi> alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, or may do very well without it. <hi>Save, Lord, ſave us from this Goſpel-Atheiſm, or we Periſh! O let not the richeſt of bleſſings, thy Goſpel-pearl, be trampled under feet in England! Whatever ſinks, Lord, raiſe the price of the Goſpel!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Inf. 5. <hi>Religion is no wrack.</hi> It has a very good <hi>action of ſlander,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt every Reproacher. Every Liar of the Legions, that report it a <hi>dark and intricate,</hi> a <hi>Knotty and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult</hi> buſineſs. For, as it has been ſhewn, it is no more, as no leſs,) then Reconciliation unto God. And an Exerciſe of our ſelves in the plain or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly particulars foreſaid; which are all our part and buſineſs. O admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Love and Grace of God, that
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:40387:60"/>ſhine in it's <hi>Brevity</hi> and <hi>Plainneſs!</hi> Our <hi>Life,</hi> is ſhort. And our <hi>Bodies</hi> eat up much of our time, in neceſſary cares for them. But the Doctrine of Reconciliation, is no tedious one. What the old <hi>Friendſhip</hi> was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and Man. How the <hi>Quarrel</hi> roſe, and how far it ran. How the <hi>Reconciliation</hi> is to be made, on Gods part, and ours; by ſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Juſtice, and ſubduing and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving our malice. Theſe things require ſhorter ſtudy, than a body of <hi>Philoſophy.</hi> Nor are they by the Holy Spirit ſet forth obſcurely. And ſo, as to require a very quick and ſubtle Wit to Underſtand them. No, <hi>a man may be wiſe unto Salvation, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wit and acuteneſs enough to make a Diſputer of this world.</hi> Nor doth Divine Kindneſs leſs ſhew it ſelf, in the <hi>Sweetneſs and Agreeableneſs</hi> of the Chriſtian Religion. Such is it's Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution we ſee, that it employs us in nothing, but moſt pleaſant Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes. In <hi>Believing</hi> and <hi>Conſidering</hi>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:40387:60"/>moſt excellent and important Truths. <hi>Labouring</hi> and <hi>Praying</hi> together for the beſt Bleſſings here. <hi>Hoping,</hi> and <hi>Joying</hi> in the hope of moſt perfect Bleſſedneſs hereafter. Is this a Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, <hi>Senſualiſts,</hi> is this an irkſome Toil? Is this, what, any thing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides <hi>affected Malignity,</hi> can ſnarl at? The <hi>Hebrews</hi> have a ſaying, <hi>An hour in Heaven is more worth then a Life on Earth.</hi> But I know thoſe that tell me, they have found more real ſolid Comfort in one hour of their <hi>Convert State</hi> on Earth, then ever they had in all their <hi>former Life.</hi> And <hi>'tis as certain that Religion is the beſt Pleaſure in this world, as that Heaven contains the best in the next world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Inf. 6. <hi>Miniſter's only buſineſs, is to make Peace.</hi> Peace and Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion between God and Men. Their buſineſs is but to promote Duty. If then Reconciliation be all Duty, all their Buſineſs muſt lie herein. In this my Text, they are called <hi>Ambaſſadors;</hi> not <hi>Heralds</hi> to proclaim War, but
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:40387:61"/>
               <hi>Embaſſadors</hi> to treat for Peace. True they muſt in order to <hi>Peace</hi> declare the <hi>War</hi> and <hi>Hoſtility</hi> between God and Sinners. It was a fooliſh Law the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> made, that no man ſhould tell his Neighbour any ill and frightful News. And they are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lepered with ignorance and Error, who would ſow up Miniſter's Mouths, and have them wholly ſilent of the Miſeries of the Unreconciled State. As though God's Peace were ever to be ſought, without Knowledge of his Wrath. Or as though they more dreaded to hear the <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> than to feel the <hi>doom</hi> thereof. Nevertheleſs, ſo it is, that the <hi>Word of God</hi> unto Miniſters committed, is the <hi>Word of Reconciliation.</hi> And Reconciliation is the work they are ſent for. They are not to <hi>preach</hi> Wrath, but in order to provoke you to <hi>fly</hi> from it. I <hi>preach Hell,</hi> (ſaid a late moſt <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher,) <hi>that you may never come there.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> I am full of wonder as I can hold. Come hear, and wonder
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:40387:61"/>with me. Earthly <hi>Kings,</hi> put out Laws; and expect their <hi>Subjects,</hi> all, ſhould, without more ado of theirs, obſerve them. They do not ſend an Officer to every <hi>Town,</hi> and <hi>Houſe</hi> to inform and perſwade the people to keep them. Eſpecially when the ſaid Laws be for the Subjects own great good! But, <hi>O admirable Benig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity!</hi> the King of Heaven puts <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents in Families,</hi> and <hi>Miniſters in Congregations?</hi> and makes it their bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs from one end of the Year to the other, to <hi>Teach</hi> and <hi>Perſwade</hi> his poor ignorant and obſtinate Subjects, to accept the Word of Reconciliation. Though the gain be only and infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theirs, not his. But I return; at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it oh <hi>Miniſters,</hi> attend it oh <hi>Parents:</hi> 'Tis the Peace of God that paſſes all Underſtanding, ſave Gods infinite one, that ye are Propoſers, Interpreters, and Orators, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents for.</p>
            <p>Higher than at Reconciliation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, you <hi>cannot</hi> aim; Lower
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:40387:62"/>you <hi>ſhould not</hi> dare to aim, Holy Angels do not want it and Devils cannot have it. But what think ye of your People and your Children? Gods Peace and Love are the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and all good; his Wrath and Curſe are the deepeſt Miſery; and there is no middle Condition. Souls reconciled, are as it were in Heaven; Souls unreconciled, are as it were in Hell. If you aim and labor at leſs then <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nconvert mens</hi> Tranſlation from the State of Wrath into the State of Peace, you are at a game of ſinful and peſtilent Foolery. You are not in the diſcharge of your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry. If you deſign not and drive not at <hi>Convert mens</hi> perſwaſion and practical improvement of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; and Hope of, and Joy in, their future complete Reconciliation: the ſame muſt be ſaid of all your pains with them. It was an ancient Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of ſome <hi>pious Fathers,</hi> to preach one part of the day for <hi>Convincing</hi> and <hi>Converting</hi> the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nregenerate;</hi> and
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:40387:62"/>the other part, for <hi>Edifying</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting</hi> the <hi>Regenerate</hi> of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations. Unto me it appears ſo wholſome a one, and uſeful, that I cannot but wiſh it in all <hi>Engliſh Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations</hi> uſed. I am aware of my unworthineſs to teach my Brethren; but as for you that are <hi>private Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> I ſhall dare to give you this Advice. <hi>Keep ye cloſeſt unto their Miniſtry, that keep cloſeſt to the buſineſs of Reconciliation in their Miniſtry.</hi> As for <hi>Preachers,</hi> bleſſed be the Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers, the Lord ſhame thoſe, that are not aſhamed to deſign no more change of their People, than <hi>Plato</hi> made of his <hi>Polemo:</hi> which was but from a <hi>Beaſt</hi> to a <hi>Man.</hi> He that <hi>Preaches not at all,</hi> and he that <hi>Preaches not the Goſpel of Reconciliation,</hi> are under the ſelf-ſame woe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16.</p>
            <p>Inf. 7. <hi>God's Rewards muſt needs be like himſelf. Great and incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</hi> If my Doctrine be true, it muſt needs be ſo. Becauſe, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that, every man muſt needs
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:40387:63"/>be a bloody <hi>Enemy</hi> of God, or an <hi>entire Friend.</hi> And if the former, <hi>Juſtice</hi> cannot but revenge it ſelf in matchleſs puniſhments: If the latter, <hi>Grace</hi> cannot but diſplay it ſelf in ſupremeſt Advancements. Neither of them are <hi>middle</hi> Relations, and neither of them can be held worthy of but <hi>middle</hi> Rewards.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> if thou haſt never done it before, come ſpend an hour now, in cloſe thinking what a <hi>Friend of God</hi> is. If thou haſt, repeat again that <hi>profitable Pleaſure.</hi> Turn back if thou remembreſt not, and ſee what Reconciliation to God is ſaid to be, in the entrance of this Diſcourſe. A ſoul that ſhould have the ſame, and no more; I mean the ſame Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with God that Man had in his firſt Eſtate, before ſin entred; he would be a rich Creature. <hi>Bare Reſtoration unto what we loſt, would be no ſmall Exaltion.</hi> But haſt thou not heard and read, what all <hi>Pulpits</hi> and <hi>Books</hi> ſpeak of our Redeemers
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:40387:63"/>ſetting Believers above that it ſelf? And bringing them into a greater nearneſs to God, then the firſt Man had to fall from. I will not follow any to be wiſe above is written in the Sacred Scripture. But from them I have long ago learned that Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers are now endeared unto God, proportionably to the value of Jeſus Chriſt's Obedience. Whereas in dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying Man before the Fall, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but ſuppoſe God to have held ſome proportion unto mans own. And conſequently, as our Saviours did unſpeakably exceed <hi>Adams</hi> Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and the <hi>Angels</hi> too: ſo the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinely vouchſafed <hi>Love</hi> unto Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, doth beyond all expreſſion ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs that which was vouchſafed unto Innocent Man. I would be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of mutual Love. A <hi>Learned Man</hi> hath conſtrued, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.10. to this purpoſe; of Chriſt's <hi>laying down his</hi> (infinitely more valuable) <hi>life for his ſheep,</hi> to the end <hi>that they might have life,</hi> (that is, all good:
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:40387:64"/>all they forfeited and loſt in the firſt <hi>Adam;) and that they might have it more abundantly</hi> (more of it than <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> ever had.) Our <hi>Engliſh Divines</hi> praiſe that Speech of a <hi>Foreigner;</hi> that <hi>God loves the pooreſt Saint on Earth better than any Angel in Heaven loves God.</hi> But I excurr no farther; I have already loſt my ſelf in aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I am thinking, what a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward this it ſelf is; and what Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and Honours muſt neceſſarily follow this. <hi>O what must be done to the man, ſo dear to the heart of God?</hi> Kings Favorites have none richer than themſelves but Kings. <hi>Gods Favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites have God infinitely, and God only more bleſſed than themſelves.</hi> Never can I raiſe my thoughts of Heaven ſo high, as when I conſider (1.) What Gods Friends are; and (2.) That Heaven's the Manſion Houſe of his Friends. Nor can I think that Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven muſt have bin what it is, if Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion had been a meer <hi>Service,</hi> and not a <hi>Friendſhip.</hi> If God had not
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:40387:64"/>been our <hi>Father,</hi> but only our <hi>Maſter!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Look we on the other ſad hand, and think what a Creature an <hi>Enemy of God</hi> is. One <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreconciled;</hi> yea and even <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreconcilable</hi> alſo. God is infinitely Holy; he hates Sin more then any Man living can hate Hell. <hi>Enmity unto him, is the very ſin of ſin: And <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreconcileableneſs is the ſoul of Enmity.</hi> What a fire in the Soul of God muſt, now, be thought to burn againſt this wight? And what a <hi>Vengeance</hi> muſt it be, which that <hi>fire</hi> executes? If the ſin for which Men are damned, was the violation of a thouſand other Laws, but not of the <hi>Law of Love;</hi> and was a collection of all other faults poſſible, beſide that of <hi>Enmity.</hi> And if Hell were the puniſhment of ſuch as had been in all other reſpects <hi>Tranſgreſſors;</hi> but had not been <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of God.</hi> I ſhould then think it a Furnace ſeven times leſs hot, then now I am able to think it. O what
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:40387:65"/>blows can Gods almighty hand give? And what ſhould hold his hand from utmoſt ſeverity, upon them with whom he is at perfect Enmity? 'Tis Sins unreconcileable Enmity, that maketh Hells eternal extremity.</p>
            <p>I. 8. <hi>There is no colour to be laid on any Temptation, againſt true Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Religion.</hi> For why? It con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in Reconciliation unto God. Awake, <hi>Reader,</hi> if thou art in a drowze. Do but awake and thou muſt needs ſee how clearly this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows. Tell me if a quarrel had riſen between a poor <hi>Subject</hi> and a mighty <hi>King.</hi> A King, and ſuch a King; and he alſo at the head of a formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable Army. And if the ſaid King ſhould ſtoop and become a ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant to his Subject for a Peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them. What could be ſaid, with <hi>any ſhew of Reaſon,</hi> to turn the poor Subject from thankful accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Kings Grace? And that upon the very firſt offer. Could the united wits of all the World make it
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:40387:65"/>look as if it were his <hi>intereſt;</hi> or ſo much as <hi>ſafe</hi> for him, to ſlight his Kings <hi>Mercy,</hi> and incenſe his <hi>Fury?</hi> No, but whatever could be ſaid, would <hi>appear,</hi> as well as <hi>be,</hi> moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd. Alas, alas! What crawling Worms are the mightieſt Earthly Kings? Worms to day, and Worms meat to morrow! But what a <hi>King</hi> is the Eternal One? What an <hi>Hoſt</hi> is he Lord of? How many Millions of holy <hi>Angels,</hi> and envious <hi>Divels</hi> hath he, that are both of them ready at his beck to tear thee in pieces? Yea, how would <hi>Frogs, Flies,</hi> or the moſt deſpicable <hi>Creatures</hi> diſpatch thee in an inſtant, if he ſhould give them Commiſſion?</p>
            <p>Two things I often wiſh. <hi>O that my Friends would never quit the truth, or abate their degree of Religion, but then when Satan can indeed preſent an appearance of gain by it.</hi> I mean, a gain of ſomewhat better, or as good as Gods Love, in their very own Thoughts. <hi>And</hi> Secondly, <hi>That
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:40387:66"/>when ever they have thought themſelves to have ſeen profit coming by it; and have by and by found their miſtake: That then they would acknowledge their horrid effaſcination; and reſolve never again to truſt the ſpectacles through which they looked unto their coſt.</hi> I know that <hi>Luſt</hi> does bewitch into <hi>Error;</hi> and <hi>Error,</hi> when it gets into the throne of the Heart, fearfully plays the <hi>Tyrant.</hi> Let Men but liſten unto their <hi>Senſes, Fancies,</hi> and <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi> they ſhall take the moſt loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome <hi>Lyes</hi> for ſelf-evident <hi>Truths:</hi> And when they have done, they ſhall be as much governed by them. They ſhall adore <hi>Dogs</hi> and <hi>Crocodiles,</hi> ſcorning <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Chriſt.</hi> They ſhall dig for a <hi>Worms</hi> favour as for immortal Treaſure; and dye away for fear of its frown. And all with unſhaken Confidence; as if <hi>God</hi> were nothing, and <hi>Idols</hi> were all things. As if the ſmiles of a mortal Man, were really a richer good then Gods Heaven; and a hard look
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:40387:66"/>from <hi>Caeſar,</hi> were more dreadful by far then Hell-fire. But I do alſo know, and I keep ſome ſtir to make others know it too: Such is the admirable <hi>conſtitution</hi> of our Religion, ſuch is its <hi>perſpicuity</hi> with its <hi>purity;</hi> that Humane Minds are not preſently ſo ſtupified, as to be unſenſible of its Glory; or ſo diſtracted, as to dream ought ſpoke againſt it, to be <hi>true,</hi> or ſo much as <hi>probable.</hi> 'Tis abundance of <hi>Opium</hi> you give your Reaſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you make it dormant enough to let an ill thought of Religion into your Heart: Before you are capable of your ſweet <hi>Follies</hi> and dear <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits.</hi> Moſt commonly, you that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect Religion, are fain to ſerve Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, without ſo much as any <hi>imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> of gain by it. I, and with many a <hi>fearful expectation</hi> of loſs too. And when your bewitched Eyes are drawn unto ſome imaginary recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence in any way of ſin; ye often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſoon afterward find the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs truth; <hi>Fraud and Frost end
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:40387:67"/>in dirt.</hi> Well were it, if then you would ſet your ſelves to verifie ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as known a ſaying; <hi>Burnt Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren dread the fire!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word: The day is coming that will reveal it. The Religion inſtituted and taught by Jeſus Chriſt, is one that Men can <hi>bray</hi> and <hi>bark</hi> againſt; as they do, and as he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told us that they <hi>would;</hi> But they cannot <hi>argue</hi> againſt. Without that <hi>quickneſs,</hi> and <hi>ſubtlety,</hi> and <hi>ſolidity,</hi> which are the priviledges of very few heads, its <hi>excellence</hi> and <hi>import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> are the plaineſt of things unto all honeſt hearts. And <hi>our Motives unto the ſevereſt Duty are ten thouſand times ſtronger then our Temptations unto the ſweeteſt Sin.</hi> He has a very hard task who goes about to prove, that I ſhall do better without Gods friendſhip then with it! That I ſhall have more Light, if I go further from the Sun!</p>
            <p>I. 9. <hi>The Kingdom of God is not Meat and Drink.</hi> Chriſtianity, or
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:40387:67"/>Goſpel ſaving Religion doth not conſiſt in external <hi>Obſervances,</hi> and little <hi>Opinions.</hi> If it be Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or a new very Friendſhip with God, it cannot ſtand in the poor deſpicable things wherein 'tis placed by too many <hi>Ceremonialiſts.</hi> I mean Ceremonialiſts of every Sect and Party among us: Many of which ſeem to value themſelves more by ſome peculiar dividing Ceremony, then by common and univerſally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>Natural <hi>corruption</hi> diſpoſes Men to allow God nothing at all, of <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection</hi> or <hi>Obedience.</hi> By Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and outward Calls of <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Parents, Miniſters,</hi> they are brought quickly unto ſhame of that <hi>open malignity.</hi> But <hi>Carnality</hi> and <hi>Sloth,</hi> admit not any great liberality to him: And <hi>Luſt,</hi> and <hi>Fancy,</hi> and <hi>ill Example,</hi> ſoon preſcribe a narrow pittance. He ſhall have <hi>outward Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage</hi> and <hi>Bodily ſervice.</hi> Preſence at the places of his Worſhip, and
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:40387:68"/>obſervation of all laudable geſtures therein. He ſhall have <hi>Lamps</hi> of Profeſſion carried for him; <hi>Oyl</hi> they cannot tend for, <hi>Graces</hi> are myſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous things. He ſhall have loud <hi>Cryes,</hi> but as for intelligent and <hi>ſincere Prayers,</hi> they promiſe him not. He ſhall have their <hi>Eyes</hi> lift up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; but he muſt excuſe them if their <hi>Affections</hi> be ſet on Earth. He ſhall have their Company at every <hi>Sacramental Feaſt;</hi> but they deſire in this thing to be forgiven, if they come having not on the <hi>Wedding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garment;</hi> and unengaged in the cares of <hi>imputed, inherent</hi> and <hi>practical</hi> Righteouſneſs. He ſhall have <hi>Zeal</hi> for the Religion they neither <hi>know</hi> nor <hi>practice;</hi> I, and it may be againſt the ſins that they do love and live in: They hope he will accept it from them, without <hi>Integrity.</hi> In ſhort; He ſhall have his <hi>Church</hi> obeyed, and <hi>Goſpel</hi> too, as far as they themſelves pleaſe: But that reaches not unto the concerns of <hi>Regeneration, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:40387:68"/>Faith, Love</hi> and <hi>Obedience,</hi> principled from them. <hi>Entering</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and <hi>keeping</hi> Covenant with him, with all the Heart, and Soul, and Strength, is that which they ſee no neceſſity of.</p>
            <p>Miſerable Creatures! Do ye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the bleſſed God to be a <hi>ſpirit</hi> or a dead <hi>ſtock?</hi> Did ye ever read one Chapter of the Holy <hi>Bible?</hi> Yea, or of the Heathen <hi>Moraliſts?</hi> Can ye in ſober ſadneſs think, that our Bleſſed <hi>Redeemer</hi> was ſent to raiſe <hi>dead ſinners,</hi> that he might make them unnatural and <hi>monſtrous Flatterers?</hi> Or that the Holy <hi>Spirit</hi> was ſent by him, to make painted Sepulchres of you? Can ye really perſwade your ſelves, that <hi>God</hi> may be honoured, and <hi>Satans Kingdom</hi> be demoliſhed, and your <hi>Souls</hi> be changed and qualified for Heaven, by your Trifling and your Lying? And without your Loving God as both your Benefactor and Ruler? <hi>O ſhut not your eyes ſo very cloſe till
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:40387:69"/>Vengeance open them for you!</hi> Look out a little; ſee my Doctrine and its Proof. It ſhall <hi>poſſeſs</hi> you of other thoughts, and <hi>rid</hi> you of theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions. It ſhall ſtop your ſcoffing at <hi>Spirituality,</hi> as a thing imaginary. At <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> and <hi>Communion with God,</hi> as though they were dreams, or but lying pretenſions of Hypocritical Men. At <hi>Gods Living in Men,</hi> and <hi>their Living in God,</hi> as though there were no ſuch things. It ſhall make you as confident as now you are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, that they are mad Men whom you hear <hi>Jearing at the Life of holy Love;</hi> and <hi>Promiſing Heaven to ever ſo little waſhed ſwine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Magna iſta credimus, quia nos parvi ſumus.</hi> Senec.</note> It ſhall make you to own, that had not your Senſe been lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, you had never took any thing but very Friendſhip with God, for honourable and great!</p>
            <p>I. 10. <hi>True Religion is its own Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi> It is ſo framed by God, that <hi>in it there is great Reward,</hi> beſides
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:40387:69"/>what is prepared for it. It is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſo, if, as our Doctrine aſſerts, it ſtands in Reconciliation and Friendſhip with God. If it be not a <hi>meer Service,</hi> but a <hi>very Friendſhip,</hi> If, as is moſt certain, God admits all his convert <hi>Servants</hi> unto the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of very <hi>Children,</hi> and the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of <hi>Friends.</hi> All and every of his Commands do refer to our good; and are framed as plainly to <hi>Delight</hi> as to <hi>Direct</hi> us. <hi>Reader,</hi> this is ſo plain in it ſelf, and from very much that has been foreſaid; that I crave thy regards but to theſe few words. Sinners generally, are full of the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that Godlineſs has all its worth but in <hi>reverſion.</hi> That let <hi>Glory</hi> be what it will, <hi>Grace</hi> is a very poor comfortleſs ſtate: And <hi>Saints,</hi> do, very commonly and moſt faultily, give them but too much occaſion ſo to imagine. They walk not on in the way to <hi>Zion</hi> with <hi>Joy and Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> They demonſtrate their very Hope but <hi>little,</hi> and their Joy <hi>leſs:</hi>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:40387:70"/>From whence 'tis inferred, their Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of Joy is <hi>none,</hi> and their hope of reverſion it ſelf is <hi>next to none.</hi> Thus prevails the evil report upon our preſent, and our promiſed <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan.</hi> And that ſo much, that the beſt Believers are <hi>profited</hi> as well as <hi>pleaſed</hi> greatly, by the Hope and Joy of thoſe few in whom both are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous. But how preſently muſt that ill report dye, were it duly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, that follows.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Grace and Glory differ but in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree.</hi> They do not ſpeak congru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, that make Glory the <hi>End,</hi> and Grace but the <hi>Means.</hi> They are ſo much <hi>one thing,</hi> that the Holy Spirit calleth them by each others names. <hi>Glory is called Grace;</hi> 1 Pet. 1.13. <hi>Hope to the end for the Grace that is to be brought unto you at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation of Jeſus Chriſt. Grace is called Glory,</hi> 2 Cor. 3.18. <hi>We are changed into the ſame image from Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Glory, even as by the Spirit of the Lord.</hi> And what think we? Is
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:40387:70"/>it a <hi>Friendſhip</hi> with himſelf through our Redeemer, that we have on earth, or no? None do or can doubt it. Is there a <hi>Reward</hi> ſweeter then of <hi>Friendſhip?</hi> I can hear of none. Is there a Friendſhip more honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able or beneficial then <hi>Gods Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> is? It were equal blaſphemy and abſurdity to dream ſo. Finally, if God be the beſt Object and all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as ſure as any; and if Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip be the beſt Enjoyment of him that Creatures can have: Wherein, ſave in degree, doth Glory exceed Grace? And if indeed Grace and Glory be for <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>kind</hi> the ſame thing; if one be Friendſhip with God <hi>begun,</hi> the other be Friendſhip with God <hi>perfected:</hi> How is it poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the ſame Man ſhould like the one and not the other?</p>
            <p>I am very certain, Men ſtand alike affected towards them, whatever they ſpeak. And <hi>were they, that here cannot be perſwaded to ſeek Gods Friendſhip of Grace, took up too unto
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:40387:71"/>Heaven; and had the door ſet wide open; and were ever ſo importunately intreated to enter in; they would not enter, no but fly back; and be, of the two, far more unwilling to take Glory above, then they are to accept of Grace here.</hi> As believing that Gods per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected Friendſhip there, would be more againſt them then his initial Friendſhip here. 'Tis equally plain, Fiſhes are moſt againſt dryeſt places, and Sinners moſt againſt the holieſt ones. As ſure as Heaven is more Holy, it is alſo more Hateful to a Sinner, then the Church ſtate below is. In a word: <hi>Heavenly Glory is not Reward, if Grace be not Reward. (Gradus ſpeciem non variat.)</hi> A hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of water is as truly water, as all that which the Sea contains. <hi>Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication above is no more truly a royalty then Reconciliation here below is.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation unto God, I mean; which is of all the works of God, if any be ſo, the moſt wonderful. For his taking Enemies and Rebels into
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:40387:71"/>Heaven when they be reconciled, is nothing ſo marvellous as his taking us into Reconciliation with him, when we are Enemies and Rebels!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> what is thy Mind, what thy Will, after all this ſaid? The <hi>Aſſent</hi> of thy Mind and <hi>Conſent</hi> of thy Will are thy greateſt acts, and moſt conſequential. All thy others be but <hi>ſuperſtructures</hi> thereon. Speak, Man, haſt thou verily <hi>Aſſented</hi> to the truth of the Goſpel in my Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; and haſt thou heartily <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented</hi> to its becoming the governing Principle of thy Life? I hope thou art not yet <hi>ignorant,</hi> and thy Head <hi>empty</hi> of the things propoſed: Nor yet <hi>obſtinate,</hi> with thy Heart <hi>full</hi> of antipathies unto them. If I may ſo ſpeak, ſome <hi>Devils have been cast out</hi> by this very Word and Prayer! Are thoſe that poſſeſs thee, of a ſort that <hi>goeth not forth ſo?</hi> Know thou, then, I will not preſently give thee over, if it be ſo. I will carry thee in fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prayers unto him, that is able
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:40387:72"/>to eaſt out the moſt pertinacious of Devils: Nor will I leave thee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out theſe parting Exhortations.</p>
            <p>Yea and I will, as for my own Life, beg and pray thee to have care of thine! Importunately (or <hi>impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently</hi> be it ſtiled,) I will beſeech thee to hear, and to come and let thee and me, be Friends with God, Bleſſed preſently and bleſſed eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally. Deſpiſe not my deſpicable appearance. My Office is honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; I ſuſtain the very <hi>perſon</hi> of God, and ſupply the <hi>place</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt. My Text warrants me to ſay it. And I muſt give thee to know, 'tis <hi>God beſeeches thee,</hi> 'tis <hi>Chriſt prays thee</hi> by theſe my Lines, to Turn and Live! Divine Authority here puts off its Terror, and <hi>for Loves ſake,</hi> intreats thee. In the <hi>Law,</hi> it thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; commands on pain of Death and Hell: Here in the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> it uſes a voice ſoft to a miracle. I never heard of a <hi>King</hi> knocking at the door of a dungeon all night long,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:40387:72"/>and calling, and crying to a <hi>Traytor</hi> to come accept a Peace and Pardon; eſpecially when he might cut off his Head, without the loſs of a Hair unto his own. But at thy door, God and Chriſt knock. To thee they have called for many a long year, it may be. Earthly Kings put out <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes,</hi> and look that every Subject ſhould look to himſelf. They do not ſend a <hi>ſtated Officer</hi> to every Town and Houſe, to put them in mind of it; to explain it; to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve caſes about it, to excite, and pray them to keep it. But God puts forth the Goſpel; and ſends out Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to do all this. Of his Love and Mercy, this he doth, as hath been foreſaid. And that charging them, with a woe denounced on their failure, to do what they can with <hi>Sheep</hi> and <hi>Lambs.</hi> And <hi>in,</hi> and <hi>out of ſeaſon;</hi> attending <hi>continually on this very thing.</hi> Withal declaring, that he will take contempt of <hi>us,</hi> as contempt of <hi>himſelf,</hi> and of his <hi>Chriſt.
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:40387:73"/>Luke</hi> 10.16. Thou art a <hi>ſtone,</hi> and not a <hi>man</hi> if thou needeſt more Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives. For God to come down from the Throne of his <hi>Soveraignty,</hi> and ſpeak Supplications, is a wonder not ſmall. For Men to make light of him and his Grace, is one truly great. <hi>Nahal</hi> ſlighted <hi>Davids</hi> kind Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage; thou ſhalt not, I hope, ſlight this that I deliver thee from thy King and Judge. No, methinks I hear thee taking up <hi>Hazaels</hi> words; <hi>Is thy Reader a Dog, that I ſhould do this thing?</hi> I proceed therefore</p>
            <p>E. 1. <hi>Reject not this doctrine of Reconciliation, though thou ſhouldſt not yet Believe it.</hi> If thou haſt read what hath been ſaid, I cannot much doubt thy Belief. But I find it ſtill good, to ſuppoſe the worſt. <hi>Some believed what the Apostles preached, and ſome believed it not.</hi> O thou that believeſt not what I have written, this I deſire from thee: Or rather, this God requires from thee; <hi>ſc.</hi> That thou abſtain from proud pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:40387:73"/>concluding, that it muſt needs be <hi>falſe,</hi> becauſe thou art not preſently perſwaded that it is <hi>true.</hi> And that thou admit it to be ſo much as <hi>doubtful,</hi> if thou canſt not yet think it <hi>certain.</hi> Worthy of thy <hi>Enquiry,</hi> if not of thy <hi>Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I pray thee believe it poſſible, that thou mayſt miſtake: And that in this very matter; wherein a miſtake is as dangerous as any where it can be. Conſequently, that it imports thee highly, to go pray God to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie thee of the Truth. And in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to thy being certified, to go to the beſt Friends thou haſt, and beſt Miniſters that thou knoweſt; and diſcourſe them concerning it; and hear what they have to offer to thee for or againſt it. I ſadly know that <hi>oftentimes it is but a Wind in the Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, that is miſtaken for a Child in the Womb:</hi> It ſtirring and moving ſo augely like a Child. I am as warie as I can: But I do, and my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence tells me I ought, to ſpeak com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:40387:74"/>to very Enquirers. I have known ſome <hi>raw Enquirers</hi> become <hi>very credible Converts</hi> in a few weeks time. And I wonder who ever knew our ignorant ſort of people become ſuch by <hi>bare Hearing,</hi> without En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring and Conſulting. I take it for granted that they receive little or no good from me, if before much time paſſes they do not come unto me. 'Tis <hi>Collocutory Preaching</hi> that God bleſſeth to ſuch: And when I have brought any of them unto that, I cannot but hope God intends them a Bleſſing. <hi>Reader,</hi> if thou art an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbeliever,</hi> I deſpair not of thee if thou beeſt but an <hi>Enquirer. Doubting uſually precedes Faith, though Faith doth not always follow Doubting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>E. 2. <hi>Delay not to ſet to the work, aſſoon as ever thou ſhalt believe the word of Reconciliation.</hi> Doſt thou alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy believe it? Thou haſt then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun thy buſineſs about it, I hope. Thou never doſt rightly Believe, till thou doſt Act. O let thy Work
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:40387:74"/>come full ſpeed after thy Faith. Get ability to tell thy <hi>God above,</hi> and (his Vicegerent,) thy <hi>Conſcience within</hi> thee; that from thy firſt Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and Perſwaſion of the truth of this Doctrine, thou didſt as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid.</hi> Make haſt, and not delay to keep his Commandments foredecla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Do not reſt, or let thy Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter reſt then, one day or hour, till thou knoweſt the <hi>Covenant of Grace</hi> and <hi>Reconciliation.</hi> Enter thee into it ſolemnly. Conſult for thy prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for the <hi>Lords Table;</hi> there to confirm it. For why, Delay is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the worſt word I have given it in my Sermon on <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.1. But now, now an <hi>hours</hi> delay is (in ſome reſpects) worſe then a <hi>years</hi> delay before. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding and Faith unimproved unto holy Practice, are the moſt horrible aggravations of ſinful Practice.</hi> But a Man is in a fair way, aſſoon as he has took but his firſt true ſtep toward Reconciliation. When he has but ſinceroly uttered
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:40387:75"/>this word; <q>Lord Jeſus I will never be my own while I breathe more; I am thine upon thy Goſpel terms for ever!</q> Be not afraid of the pain of this. 'Tis a ſhort one, and preſently turns to Joy. As the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of ſin be ſhort, and quickly turn to Plagues. When that is but rightly ſaid, the wheels will run in all other work.</p>
            <p>Haſt, haſt my Reader. If Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians had given thee over for a dead Man, wouldſt then Delay? The dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing people I am called to, be all for preſent Peace with God. The moſt healthful of the Living have full as much reaſon to be for it. O that I could not ſay, I ſee them otherwiſe minded. I have read of <hi>Indian Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners,</hi> chained in golden ſetters: And I ſee many Engliſh ones, whoſe Eſtates on Earth allow them not lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or liberty for Peace-making with Heaven. I tell them in my plaineſs, that the Dogs in <hi>Sicily</hi> cannot hunt, becauſe the ſweet flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:40387:75"/>in every field overcome the ſcent. And that the ſweets of this World in which they live, do ſpoil their ſcent and ſavour of Spiritual things, and keep them from following after their Peace with God. And for <hi>poor peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> how little haſt, do all their hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips below, provoke them to make for the Treaſure above. <hi>Rich</hi> and <hi>Poor</hi> are, both, in expectation, as they tell us, of Eternal Happineſs. Both believe Reconciliation, hereto neceſſary. But alas, both do not haſten to get it made; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore great is the miſery of both upon them.</p>
            <p>E. 3. <hi>Let the buſineſs of thy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation have all thy ſtrength ſpent on it, when thou haſt ſet unto it. Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> Heard I not thee ſaying ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while; <q>Here begins my eſſay of Reconciliation unto my offended God?</q> Thou art at it, art thou not? If ſo, the <hi>Father of Glory</hi> be thy good ſpeed? But as ever thou expecteſt him to be ſo, ſpare for no
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:40387:76"/>pains therein. O what does <hi>require,</hi> or what will <hi>requite</hi> thy pains, if Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation unto God will not?</p>
            <p>Tell me, Man, doth the Goſpel bid thee <hi>play,</hi> or <hi>work out</hi> thy Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion! And doth it account that to be a Play, or a Work of thine, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou putteſt not forth <hi>all</hi> thy ſtrength. All thy <hi>contriving,</hi> and all thy <hi>executing</hi> ſtrength. Verily <hi>in Gods eſteem, it is idly done, whatever thou haſt not forelaid with beſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, and brought forth with thy utmoſt might.</hi> Thou doſt but trifle, till it comes to that paſs, that thou mayſt truly ſpeak thus. <q>Of all things under the Sun my <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding</hi> doth conſult moſt; my <hi>Will</hi> doth command moſt; my <hi>Practick, Powers</hi> do put forth themſelves moſt of all, for my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation with God. I <hi>Project</hi> nothing, I <hi>Crave</hi> nothing, I <hi>Labour</hi> for nothing <hi>comparably</hi> unto it; or for any thing, but <hi>reductively</hi> and <hi>ſubordinately</hi> unto it. A weak Mind,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:40387:76"/>a weak Heart, and weak Practick power, I muſt own mine to be. Weak in themſelves, and weak in compariſon of many other Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. But, my Heart in this thing reproaches me not; <hi>I am throughout Predominantly for Reconciliation.</hi> Nor doth my Mind plod and ſtudy, nor my Heart chuſe and crave, nor my Hands more follow their work for any thing to be named, than for this Reconciliation. I am ſure I do jealouſly watch my Heart daily. And deſire to expend my <hi>whole ſtrength</hi> in the matter of my Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cillation, which is now my <hi>whole Buſineſs.</hi> I do believe, <hi>God's peace is attainable by a restleſs Devil, as ſoon as by an idle Man.</hi> And it is, and is like to be my care all days of my Life, that God may never hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth call me <hi>wicked</hi> or <hi>ſhalthful</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant. In this I will follow <hi>Calvin,</hi> as <hi>Calvin</hi> followed Chriſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>E. 4. <hi>Let a Strength greater than thy own be invoked, while thou art ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:40387:77"/>thy own in the buſineſs of Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation.</hi> Reader, know'ſt not thou how in all things to proſper? Come, and Learn! <hi>Be much upon thy knees, then ſhalt thou ſucceed in every work of thy Hands.</hi> Of all the works there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, Reconciliation is the greateſt. Wherefore, of all the ſame, beg the greateſt help and aid of God for this. And with the greateſt Faith and Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vence beg it. <hi>Prayer, is an Incenſe made of all Spices;</hi> all Graces are In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients in it. Some ſay, it has more Promiſes in the word made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, than any other Duty hath. I am ſure it hath ſo many made to it, when it is made it ſelf with Faith and Fervour, that it muſt needs receive whatever it asks. True; <hi>Prayer doth not excuſe our Labour. Praying, and doing no more, againſt Iniquity, is it ſelf a black myſtery of Iniquity.</hi> God will not have our Sins mortified for us, as <hi>Goliah</hi> was killed for the <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> we, like them, looking on, but ſtriking not one ſtroke. But
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:40387:77"/>yet good is the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Proverb; <hi>Without ſtanding Prayer, the World could not ſtand.</hi> A World of Pains is loſt for want of Prayers. In its own place; <hi>Our own Prayer is as neceſſary as God's Power, for our welfare,</hi> His Power it is, that Works, Upholds, Encreaſes all Good: But our Prayer it is, that he will have to fetch it. If we will have that his Power, he will ordinarily make us come and fetch it by Prayer. Indeed, he may <hi>Give,</hi> but we may not <hi>Expect,</hi> before, and without our asking. And you ſhall ordinarily find it, eſpecially as to ſenſible returns; that God meaſures his <hi>Grant of Prayers,</hi> by <hi>our care in Prayers.</hi> And when we exceed in our <hi>Cares,</hi> God exceedeth in his <hi>Grants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> do but thus Pray always, I will be content to bear thy Curſe, if thou doſt not proſper always. But, <hi>I will as ſoon be bound for thy Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Life without thy Breathing, as for thy reconciled one without thy Praying.</hi>
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:40387:78"/>Come on, I pray thee, and let thou and I, enter the Holy Order of <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieants; God's Beggers be richer than Lords and Ladies.</hi> I uſe to beſeech <hi>poor folk,</hi> to let me make them rich; and <hi>rich people,</hi> to let me make them richer. Yea, both to let me make them <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Queens.</hi> And how, thinkeſt thou? Why by <hi>Marrying</hi> and <hi>Begging.</hi> I have known thoſe that have enriched themſelves more by a happy <hi>Match,</hi> than by all the <hi>Trade</hi> they ever drove in their Lives. Let Souls but Marry Jeſus Chriſt, they ſhall be ſure to do it. Yea, and by <hi>Petitions</hi> granted at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> many have ſweetly advanced them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in this World. Let us both keep Petitioning and Begging hard at the Throne of Grace, we ſhall not fail of Favour and Advancement in a Higher Court than <hi>White-Hall.</hi> Shrink not then, my Reader, but come on, and reſolve moſt reſolutely, and ſay: <q>O Prayer, I do now ſee what thou art. And I reſolve what
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:40387:78"/>in all my Life thou ſhalt be. I will leſs uſe <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Salt,</hi> than <hi>Prayer;</hi> and leſs delightfully, as far as I am able. Prayer ſhall be the <hi>Girdle</hi> compaſſing all my Affairs; ſmall and great. I will never think any Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to hang ſo low, that I may reach it ſafely enough, without ſetting up the Ladder of Prayer. And as for Mercies of the <hi>Higher Hemiſphere;</hi> as for my Reconciliation unto God, that is one and all Mercies; <hi>If I forget Prayer, let my Tongue cleave to the roof of my Mouth.</hi> For this, with the Trumpet of Prayer will I daily Alarm <hi>Heaven;</hi> call God my Saviour to my Succor; and Storm <hi>Hell</hi> to its Terror. Being the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of my Reconciliation cannot be ſcattered till God ariſe; and God will not ariſe, till Prayer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakes him; <hi>Heaven ſhall as ſoon be without Angels Praiſes, as without my Prayers ringing there.</hi> In the Mount and Valley, at my beſt and at my worſt, I will Pray. <hi>Ephraim</hi> and
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:40387:79"/>
                  <hi>Manaſſes</hi> were <hi>Brothers.</hi> And I know <hi>when I am in Plenty, I am in danger of Forgetfulneſs.</hi> But I will beſeech God that I may never know any <hi>Plenty</hi> but a Praying one; or <hi>Poverty,</hi> but what may encreaſe my Beggery at his Door. And that ſtill, whatever it be he ſpreads my Table with, I may never come more hungrily to my <hi>Supper</hi> than to my <hi>Prayer.</hi> O my Soul, <hi>the Door of Mercy ſtands open continually,</hi> may the Mouth of thy Prayer ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verkeep ſhut. And mayſt thou never ceaſe to be <hi>Prayerful,</hi> till God doth to be <hi>Bountiful.</hi>
               </q> He is not like the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Prince, that would not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the <hi>Chineſes</hi> into his preſence, without their ſubmitting firſt to an hundred Baſtinadoes on their Bodies. No; at the Court of Heaven they are made moſt welcom, that come to Petition. And the greater Bleſſings they do ask, the greater welcom they have. Ask a Kingdom, thou ſhalt be more pleaſing to God than if
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:40387:79"/>thou beg but a piece of Bread.</p>
            <p>E. 5. <hi>For your Life, deſpiſe not mens help, while you do drive on Prayer for Gods Grace.</hi> Reader, hearken to a Man that every week ſees ſad inſtances. Some poor Souls, awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unto a like care of their Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, do go (as they do tell me) unto their prayers. And, ſuch as they be, do <hi>abound</hi> indeed in them. Of <hi>God,</hi> they know little. Of the <hi>Covenant of Grace,</hi> and its terms on which God will accept them. and on no other, they are ignorant ſorely. Yea, and many of them, are ſenſible that they are ſo; and go about wiſhing, <hi>O that I did know God better, and what it is he would have me to do!</hi> But they have no Friend unto whom they can get themſelves to confeſs this igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, None at leaſt, that is able to inſtruct them. <hi>Pride</hi> indeed, tho' they name it ſhamefacedneſs, makes them keep it to themſelves. When any motion of God's Spirit, by <hi>legal Terror,</hi> puts them upon going to
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:40387:80"/>ſome Miniſter, and opening their Caſe unto him, <hi>Satan</hi> finds it no hard matter to make them ſtifle it ſoon; and this very <hi>often,</hi> and very <hi>long.</hi> Under the Dominion of this <hi>dumb Devil,</hi> ſome tell me they have been for many <hi>Months,</hi> and ſome for <hi>Years</hi> together. Though in the mean time they have had ſhrewd <hi>Conflicts;</hi> and have gone near to gain <hi>Conquest</hi> ſometimes. They have gone, and knock'd at Miniſters doors with a purpoſe to confeſs ignorance and beg inſtruction; and yet have had their hearts fail; have turned away and not entered into the Houſes, but gone back drooping unto their Homes. It is ſuggeſted, and ſoon ſurmiſed by them, that Miniſters and Friends will <hi>Chide</hi> them, <hi>Shame</hi> them, and <hi>Grieve</hi> them, who think they have Grief e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough on their Hearts alreatly. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, that God is the beſt Toucher and Helper; and can Help and Teach without Friends and Miniſters. I, and is merciful and ready to do ſo for
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:40387:80"/>ſuch as do pray ſo much to him as they do. Yea, and will not upbraid neither, as Men will. Hereupon they keep ſtill themſelves unto themſelves. Make no uſe of them to whom God has committed the <hi>word of Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> for its Deſpenſation unto them. And given <hi>the Tongue of the Learned, to ſpeak a word in Seaſon.</hi> They hear indeed their Sermons and continued Diſcourſes: But how? Much, they do <hi>not underſtand.</hi> Much, they <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtand.</hi> Little, they <hi>Remember.</hi> Moſt, or all, they <hi>miſapply</hi> to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Every Threat they hear, they ſay they muſt <hi>Deſpair.</hi> Every promiſe they hear, their Caſe is as good as the beſt they <hi>proſume.</hi> Thus are they up and down, like the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled Sea. To the <hi>Priests Lips,</hi> to the <hi>Miniſters</hi> Face apart, they will not go. <hi>Collocutory preaching,</hi> they think, will kill them; be it from Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters or, any Religious Friends. I muſt not ſay what I know, of the gain and the joy of many, when
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:40387:81"/>their proud Stomachs have once come down; and they have conſented to bear the ſmart of its being known what they have been. But I very boldly tell thee, Reader, all that I have met with, have in vain cryed and prayed and expected God's <hi>imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Teachings.</hi> And have multiplied ſins and ſorrows by their diſuſe of his <hi>appointed Teachings</hi> through the Mouths of his Miniſters and People. Never lighting into the way of God, or Knowing and Taſting his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, till they had made uſe of the Counſellors inſtituted by God for them. And become Companions of ſuch as fear God, Walking with people wiſe to Salvation, and asking and borrowing Wiſdom from them. Leaving and Loathing the Society of vain and vile Creatures, that former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly corrupted and hardened them. Now rejoycing ſingly in ſuch as do <hi>Instruct, Exhort, Reprove,</hi> and <hi>Give Examples</hi> of Good.</p>
            <p>Others alſo, God's Holy <hi>Segullas,</hi>
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:40387:81"/>and Choice Children (I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) there are, who ſin in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect. Sound <hi>Converts,</hi> yea conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Proficients</hi> in Grace and Peace. Who by one or other Temptation, are turned aſide from all Sociable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Converſe with their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. And from a juſt Freedom of Diſcourſe with their Paſtors. Of their Brethren, they ſeem to think ſome too much <hi>above</hi> them in Gifts and Graces, for their Communion. Tho' one would think, a poor body ſhould not care how rich his Friends were. They will be the more help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful unto him; will they not? But, alas, theſe ſeem to fear, they will be the <hi>more Scornful,</hi> and <hi>leſs Helpful.</hi> And for others, they appear to judge too much <hi>below</hi> them. Too dull in their Underſtandings for them to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct. Too looſe in their Lives, for them to Reclaim. They ought to conſider, that the more <hi>dark</hi> their Brethren be, they may the better ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect welcom to that ſmall Light they
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:40387:82"/>can Miniſter. And the <hi>colder</hi> their Religious Love is, there's the more need of their Bellows whatever they are, to blow it up. But this is not conſidered, and Converſe with theſe is not maintained. Yea, ſadly be it ſaid as the very Truth is, Their Communion with their Brethren in Chriſt, as ſuch, is next to none. However, theſe ſo faulty Chriſtians perſevere in Prayer and Supplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>Publick, Family, Cloſet-prayers.</hi> And even <hi>Ejaculatory</hi> ones. But theſe, ſeven theſe Souls; praying, and praying theſe, all ſorts of prayer; theſe, many, moſt, all of them (for ought I know) have their ſore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes from on High. Walk about with <hi>Hannah</hi>'s ſorrowful Spirit, for their ungranted Suits, as they teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, many of them with their own Mouths. Long they have walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the dark, ſeen no light of God's reconciled Face, and it has been as much as they could do to live, for his Terrors upon them. Nor hath he
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:40387:82"/>ever ſhone upon their Souls, or ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken peace; until they have took ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and a better courſe. Until they have ſhook off their <hi>ſullenneſs,</hi> and became <hi>Affable</hi> and <hi>Courteous.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving it God's way, very often to utter <hi>his voice</hi> through <hi>Good mens mouths.</hi> Both his <hi>Teaching, Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling,</hi> and <hi>Comforting</hi> voice. Yea, and to make none of his Children, ſo <hi>Fat</hi> as thoſe that are <hi>liberal</hi> to their Brothers and Siſters. To <hi>water</hi> none, ſo much as thoſe that <hi>water others.</hi> They themſelves do tell me, God hath made their <hi>going</hi> unto their Godly Friends, a ſenſible going unto him. Their <hi>hearing</hi> of them, a hearing of him. I, and their <hi>helping</hi> of them, a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty help (of God's making) unto themſelves. In a word, Uniting to the <hi>Members,</hi> to be Uniting unto Chriſt himſelf the <hi>Head.</hi> They tell me, they have at laſt found, that God <hi>ſpeaks</hi> by Mens Mouths, and <hi>works</hi> by Mens Hands. And to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect <hi>Miniſters,</hi> or <hi>private Christians</hi>
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:40387:83"/>help, is to neglect God's own help and Grace. Be it then, Reader, an Immortal Maxim with thee and me: that <hi>Religious Friendſhip with good Men, and mutual Conference, is a means or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by God, for Aſſurance and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance.</hi> And, let us cheriſh <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> Friendſhip, as moſt neceſſary unto <hi>Divine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>E. 6. <hi>When thou art reconciled, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile thy Brethren.</hi> I will be ſhort in this my laſt Exhortation. In which my meaning is, that you ſhould do your beſt, to bring your Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons into the ſtate you find good. I know 'tis next to impoſſible, to <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy</hi> and not <hi>Commend</hi> Reconciliation unto ones <hi>Children</hi> and <hi>Houſehold.</hi> Directions and Motives I have elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where given, and am by promiſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to ſend abroad. In this place, I ſay but this. Good Reader, give it good attention. <hi>Reconciled Souls be all Love.</hi> Souls made after his heart, who has wrote himſelf by the name of Love. <hi>Love is all Action.</hi> As
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:40387:83"/>well thou mayſt hold all the four Winds in a bag, as Love in a ſleep. For, like Fire, as long as it Lives, it Acts. <hi>Reaſon, Love, and Religion, is all religious Loves Communication.</hi> Theſe, religious Love is ever drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, nor hath it more to inſtill. He that Loves me, muſt ſhew it by eſſays to make me Wiſer in my ſelf, more Kind to him and to all Men, more Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful unto God. The two former are the <hi>means,</hi> the laſt is the <hi>end.</hi> Unleſs theſe be the daily Exerciſes of thy <hi>Life,</hi> there's ſmall appearance of thy <hi>reconciled ſtate.</hi> If thou art in it, thou walkeſt unworthy of it; making Men juſtly to <hi>doubt</hi> it, and provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king God moſt dreadfully to <hi>cloud</hi> it. Remember that I told thee; <hi>if thou haſt but ſmall care of thy Families Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation, God ſeems to have no ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving care of thine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> The God of Heaven looks down, to ſee if <hi>any,</hi> in particular if <hi>thou</hi> that art here reading, wilt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed be Reconciled unto him, or
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:40387:84"/>no! He declares, if thou wilt <hi>take hold of his ſtrength, that thou mayſt make peace with him, thou ſhalt make peace with him.</hi> If thou wilt not, his <hi>Vengeance</hi> is ready for thoſe, that for <hi>Reconciliation</hi> will not be ready. So he commands me once more to tell thee: That if thou haſt ſtood out <hi>unto this laſt Call,</hi> thou mayſt not alſo ſtand out <hi>beyond</hi> it. If thou doſt not, but ſhalt be by theſe laſt Lines perſwaded to take Gods offer, the <hi>richeſt Treaſures</hi> of his Eternal Love ſhall be thy <hi>Reward.</hi> If not, the Lord ſend thee quickly ſome <hi>Lines</hi> or <hi>Sounds,</hi> that he will work by, more then by mine! I know not how to leave thee. And therefore I will add this; if thou doſt but ſo much as <hi>fear</hi> now thy Unreconciled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; if that Fear of mine become thine own Fear, that Fear of thine will become my Hope. My Hope that Reconciliation work is beginning.</p>
            <p>But as for many <hi>Readers,</hi> I will hope them <hi>Converts.</hi> That have caſt
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:40387:84"/>themſelves down at Gods <hi>Mercy-ſeat,</hi> and humbled themſelves at his <hi>Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtool.</hi> That have turned unto him with <hi>full purpoſe</hi> of Heart, and made with him a <hi>ſolemn Covenant.</hi> That have took him to be their <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Father,</hi> and devoted themſelves to be his <hi>Servants</hi> and <hi>Children.</hi> That have received Chriſt Jeſus in all his <hi>Offices,</hi> and ſtand bent to walk with him in all his <hi>ways.</hi> And all this up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a holy change of <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>Inclination.</hi> Not upon a meer <hi>fright,</hi> and new ſenſe, of their (otherwiſe) dangerous Condition. I will hope that many are Reconciled unto God truly. That they are got to the end of their <hi>Greation,</hi> the Enjoyment of God. To the end and deſign of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and its <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> Reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation unto him. That they have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained unto that of God, which is, and will for ever be, <hi>enough,</hi> and even <hi>all</hi> unto them. Enough, in the <hi>abſence of Creature comforts,</hi> as the Sun is light enough without Candles
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:40387:85"/>or Stars. Enough in the <hi>confluence of Worldly Troubles;</hi> as the Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Plate and Jewel is enough, when all the Farthings in the Houſe are ſtolen. I will hope that many are ſaying moſt gladly to this effect. <q>There's no <hi>Neutrality.</hi> God is <hi>for</hi> or <hi>againſt</hi> every Man: And e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Man either <hi>hates</hi> God, as if he were evil; or <hi>loves</hi> him more then he allows himſelf to love his own Soul! An hour or two agoe, God was my Enemy and I his. Now he Loveth mee, and I Love him. O what a <hi>Hell</hi> am I raiſed from? What an <hi>Heaven</hi> am I raiſed to? True, I had a <hi>ſort of Peace</hi> with God before; but it was but a <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption</hi> that I was dropping into Hell with. <hi>I had the evidences of Hell in my Forehead, while I had the dreams of Heaven in my Brain.</hi> I had a <hi>ſort of Peace</hi> with my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; but it was but a <hi>Truce.</hi> One, wherein it was all the while
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:40387:85"/>preparing torments for me. Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that have, and would have more, filled my <hi>Heart</hi> with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, my <hi>Eyes</hi> with tears, my <hi>Tongue</hi> with complaints. My eaſe was but that of a <hi>drunken Sleep,</hi> not the true one of <hi>ſound Health.</hi> The work of this day, the work of my Life-time, yea the work of my Eternity, will be to bleſs and magnifie my <hi>Reconciled God,</hi> and my <hi>Reconciling Advocate. Chriſt,</hi> my Advocate, pleading in his own perſon what he has paid for me. And the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> my Advocate, teaching me to plead it with God, and with my ſelf!</q>
            </p>
            <p>I have read that St. <hi>Jerome</hi> had always Chriſts call unto <hi>Judgment</hi> ringing in his head. <hi>Reader, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> may his call unto <hi>Reconciliation</hi> be ever ringing in thine! One of our <hi>Engliſh Martyrs</hi> dyed with his Pardon by him; he would not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:40387:86"/>it on the <hi>ill terms</hi> whereon it was offered. But O burn thou not in Hell, for not accepting the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don that God offers thee; they are <hi>good terms</hi> whereon his Offers be made. It is wonderfully low that God doth condeſcend in them. Thou canſt not ſay wherein thou canſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire lower Condeſcention. 'Tis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, that a Gentleman once pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his King to give him leave; and offered at a dear rate to buy his leave; to come ſometimes into his preſence, and cry, <hi>God ſave the King!</hi> And being asked his reaſon, made anſwer, that (whether the King loved him or no,) he ſhould gain enough by it, if, by that means, he gat the report of being beloved much by the King. Great reaſon there is for our fear, that many Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors do aim at no more. That they enter <hi>Church fellowſhip,</hi> follow <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,</hi> open their <hi>Ears</hi> to Sermons, and their <hi>Purſes</hi> unto the Preachers;
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:40387:86"/>and all to gain but <hi>the repute of being reconciled</hi> unto God. Not making very Reconciliation it ſelf, their ſcope and drift; the <hi>End of their Actions,</hi> and (as then it would be) <hi>the Rule of their Deſires. Reader,</hi> ſay that I warned thee againſt this moſt hyper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical Folly. I beſeech thee, <hi>Live for ſomewhat more than a Lye. For ſomewhat more than a Name to live, and that a falſe one alſo.</hi> Wilt thou not be perſwaded? I pray thee, Man, think a thought or two, of the <hi>ſhort Continuance</hi> of this poor Name it ſelf. Of its very <hi>ſlight airy and ſmoky Pleaſure.</hi> I, and of its certain <hi>attendant Torments.</hi> For though thou tryeſt a thouſand ways to diſarm thy Conſcience, thou ſhalt not avoid it, but ſhalt ever and anon have wounds that will marr thy Mirth. And give thee Torments, ſtronger then thy De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights.</p>
            <pb n="166" facs="tcp:40387:87"/>
            <p>If all will not move thee: But thou hardeneſt thy Heart againſt all, and art reſolute againſt Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilement unto God. What remains, but that I ſay, as a <hi>Pious Matron,</hi> once did to a long <hi>Prodigal Son?</hi> To this effect. <q>You have a long time grieved and plagued my Soul with your ſin. I have call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, counſelled, and begged you to Convert. I have wept, and mourned, and cryed to God night and day. Impatient of the thoughts of your Damnation. But now, being nothing prevails, and I ſee no hope. Now, I do (as I ought) even ſit down content. I, now, conſent to thy being Damned. Let God deſtroy thee, if he pleaſe, in his Righteous Fury; ſeeing thou wilt not accept of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling Mercy. With all my Heart, God do his will with thee.</q> It is ſaid, that by theſe laſt forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming Prints of the Mothers heart,
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:40387:87"/>the Sons wicked one was broken. That by theſe words, ſet home by Gods Spirit, he was Converted and became an eminent Servant of our Bleſſed Saviour. God give alike efficacy unto theſe Lines of mine.</p>
            <p>Heavenly <hi>Luther</hi> profeſſed that the Article of <hi>Juſtification</hi> reigned in his Heart. It is the more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive Article of <hi>Reconciliation,</hi> that I wiſh reigning in the Hearts of all the Miniſters and Chriſtians of <hi>England.</hi> Some have called it <hi>the richeſt Vein in the whole Mine of Goſpel treaſure.</hi> But (as I hope, I have proved it,) I boldly name it <hi>one and all.</hi> Even, <hi>the whole Mine of Gods Mercy, and the whole Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of Mans Duty.</hi> There are thoſe abroad, who count us <hi>narrow ſouls,</hi> as many as confine our cares and pains unto this Argument. But <hi>we think we have the Spirit of God,</hi> to whom they pretend not; and <hi>do
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:40387:88"/>walk at large,</hi> while they underſtand it not. <hi>God knows, the Goſpel teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies, and the Day will reveal the truth.</hi> I conclude with this appeal, made unto all that have but any tolerable Religious eye-ſight.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <hi>Whether a little Religion does not go a great way, among them who make not Reconciliation their firſt, middle, and laſt work?</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:40387:88"/>
            <head>Books lately Publiſhed by Mr. <hi>Daniel Burgeſs,</hi> and are to be Sold by <hi>Thomas Park hurſt,</hi> at the Bible and Three Crowns in <hi>Cheapſide.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>A Call to Sinners, ſuch as are under ſentence of Death, and ſuch as are under any proſpect of it from the long ſuffering, and gracious, but moſt righteous God.</item>
               <item>Three Queſtions reſolved briefly and plainly, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. What Conceptions ought we to have of the bleſſed God? 2. What are thoſe Truths, whereof the Knowledge appeareth moſt indiſpenſably ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary unto our Salvation; and (therefore) to be firſt and moſt learnt by us? 3. What is the change wrought in a Man by Gods H. Word and Spirit, before he can ſafely conclude himſelf paſſed from Death to Life? Being the Summ of three Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</item>
               <item>The Chriſtian Temper: Or, the Quiet ſtate of Mind that Gods Servants labour for. Set forth in a Sermon at the Funeral of Mrs. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſula Collins.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A ſeaſonable Queſtion plainly reſolved, <hi>(viz.)</hi> What are we to judge of their ſpiritual eſtate who neglect the Lords Supper.</item>
               <item>And what is that diſcerning of the Lords Body in it, without which men do Eat and Drink their own Damnation.</item>
               <item>The Chriſtians earneſt Expectation and Longing for the Glorious Appearing of the great God and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt. Set forth in a Diſcourſe occaſioned by the Deceaſe of that Excellent Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian and Miniſter of Chriſt, Mr. <hi>Noah Webb,</hi> late of <hi>Sandhurſt</hi> in the County of <hi>Berks.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:40387:89"/>
               <head>Some Books ſold by <hi>John Lawrance</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>SEveral Diſcourſes; <hi>viz.</hi> I. Of Purity and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. II. Of Repentance. III. Of ſeeking firſt the Kingdom of God; By <hi>Hezekiah Burton.</hi> D.D. Publiſhed by Dean <hi>Tillotſon.</hi> Octavo.</item>
               <item>The Triumphs of Grace: Or, the laſt words and edifying death of the Lady <hi>Margaret de la Muſſe,</hi> a Noble <hi>French</hi> Lady, who dyed <hi>May</hi> 1681. Aged only 16 years. Twelves.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clavis Grammatica:</hi> Or the ready way to the Latin Tongue, containing moſt plain demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the regular Tranſlating of Engliſh into Latin; by <hi>F. B.</hi> School-maſter in <hi>London.</hi> Octavo.</item>
               <item>Orbis Imperantis Tabellae Geographico, Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co, Geneologico, Caronologicae, in quibus Geogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiae Epitome Mappis quo fieri potuit exactiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, deſcriptio Hiſtorica Imperiorum, Regnorum, &amp; Rerum Publicarum, ſeculorum ſeries a Chriſto Nato ad hunc uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> An. 1685. On Copper Plates. Octavo.</item>
               <item>A Relation of the Conqueſt of <hi>Florida</hi> by the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> To which is added, Two Journeys of the preſent Emperor of <hi>China</hi> into <hi>Tarcary</hi> in 1682, 1683. Octavo.</item>
               <item>A Help to true Spelling and Reading, with a Scripture Catechiſm. By <hi>William Scoffia.</hi> Octavo.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:40387:89"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
